<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning God's judgements resolving many weighty questions and cases relating to them. Preached (for the substance of it) at Old Swinford in Worcester-shire: and now publish'd to accompany the annexed narrative, concerning the man whose hands and legs lately rotted off: in the neighbouring parish of Kings-Swinford, in Staffordshire; penned by another author. / by Simon Ford ...</title>
            <author>Ford, Simon, 1619?-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1484</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28411</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10590308</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10590308</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45297</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39910)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45297)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1383:37 or 1777:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning God's judgements resolving many weighty questions and cases relating to them. Preached (for the substance of it) at Old Swinford in Worcester-shire: and now publish'd to accompany the annexed narrative, concerning the man whose hands and legs lately rotted off: in the neighbouring parish of Kings-Swinford, in Staffordshire; penned by another author. / by Simon Ford ...</title>
                  <author>Ford, Simon, 1619?-1699.</author>
                  <author>Illingworth, James, d. 1693. A just narrative or account of the man whose hands and legs rotted off.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 64, [4], 12, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.C. for Henry Brome, at the Gun at the West-end of St. Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A just narrative or account of the man whose hands and legs rotted off" has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library and Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Duncalf, John, d. 1677.</term>
               <term>Providence and government of God.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45297:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45297:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Concerning God's Judgments; Reſolving many weighty <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ESTIONS</hi> and <hi>CASES</hi> Relating to them. Preached (for the ſubſtance of it) at <hi>OLD SWINFORD</hi> IN <hi>WORCESTER-SHIRE:</hi> And now publiſh'd to accompany The annexed <hi>NARRATIVE,</hi> Concerning the Man whoſe <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Legs</hi> lately <hi>rotted off:</hi> In the neighbouring Pariſh of <hi>KINGS-SWINFORD,</hi> IN <hi>STAFFORD-SHIRE;</hi> Penned by another <hi>Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>SIMON FORD,</hi> D. D. and <hi>Rector</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Pariſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>A. C.</hi> for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the Gun at the Weſt-end of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:45297:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Sept. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>T. Turner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:45297:2"/>
            <head>To his Honoured Friends, <hi>THOMAS TOLEY</hi> OF KEDERMINSTER; AND <hi>PHILIP TOLEY</hi> OF PRESTWOOD-HALL, <hi>Eſquires.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THat I joyn both your Names in one <hi>Dedication,</hi> is not barely becauſe you are <hi>Brethren,</hi> both in <hi>Nature,</hi> and endeared <hi>affection</hi> each to other: but alſo, becauſe you have been, and ſtill are ſo, in the particular kindneſſes you have for me, and my labours. For I gratefully acknowledge, that from the free and unexpected donation of the <hi>elder</hi> of you, I am fixed in this Sphere wherein I now move: and from the <hi>others</hi> near neighbourhood I receive conſtant expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of a more than ordinary value for my Miniſtry. And withal, knowing the great
<pb facs="tcp:45297:3"/>Influence both your Names have on thoſe parts, to the benefit of which eſpecially the following Papers are deſigned; I thought it neceſſary in the publication of them to deſire your joint-countenance in the <hi>recommendation</hi> of them to your many <hi>Tenants</hi> and <hi>Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants.</hi> A requeſt, which I doubt not to obtain from you, becauſe I know both your hearts are already poſſeſſed with a juſt vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of that great Providence which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned them, and an hearty deſire that all thoſe who any way relate to you may be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered thereby.</p>
            <p>Which Providence, as it filled all theſe parts, and thence the whole Nation, for ſome months, with diſcourſe and wonder; and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed the curioſity of all inquiſitive Perſons, whoſe occaſions brought them near the place where it was acted; and I hope hath contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted towards the edification of many of them. So the conſideration thereof excited me to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to render it more ſerviceable to that great End. This I endeavoured lately, by preaching ſeveral Sermons relating to that occaſion, to my own Congregation, who had generally been led either by their Curioſity, or better Motives (as it is to be hoped of divers of them) to the ſight of that ſad ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle, expoſed by the Divine Majeſty to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick view ſo near their own habitations: and afterwards upon the declared opinion of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Judicious Auditors, that they might be
<pb facs="tcp:45297:3"/>more publickly uſeful, reviewed them, and fitted them, as well as ſuch plain Country Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes could be, without wholly altering the frame of them, for the Preſs.</p>
            <p>And this I did, the rather becauſe they were thought fit by the Reverend Author of the annexed Narrative in particular, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company it into the world; which he therefore ſent to me, that I might ſo annex it; and withal, might farther aſſiſt it to the obtaining its honeſt end, by my atteſtation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>former</hi> of theſe (though he needs it not) I do hereby readily give him, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured by unqueſtionable Teſtimony, (though I my ſelf was out of the Country, during the greateſt part of the time wherein that ſad Providence was acting) that the ſubſtance of what he relates is exactly True, and concerning the Particulars, (ſeeing they are averred upon his own Perſonal knowledge, who by occaſion of the nearneſs of his reſidence, being within the bounds of the ſame Pariſh, was the moſt frequent Viſitor of the Party whoſe condition he relates) no man can ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally doubt, who knows him, (as you both have for many years) or will but ask a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of him from you.</p>
            <p>The <hi>latter,</hi> becauſe I need not give it as to you, to whom the knowledge of the <hi>Author</hi> himſelf ſufficiently recommends it; and yet I deſire to give it to others by you; and beg the
<pb facs="tcp:45297:4"/>ſame again my ſelf from you on the behalf of the <hi>diſcourſe</hi> prefixed, which (as being more properly mine own) I hereby conſign, with my ſelf, to your ſervice, as being,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honoured Sirs, </salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate and obliged Servant in the work of the Lord Jeſus, <hi>SIMON FORD.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Old</hi> Swinford, <date>Sept. <hi>20. 1677.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45297:4"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Readers of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and the annexed Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: Eſpecially the Inhabitants of <hi>Old Swinford</hi> and <hi>Kings-Swinford,</hi> with the Town of <hi>Sturbridge,</hi> and the adjacent Pariſhes and Hamlets.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Readers, and eſpecially you of this Neighbourhood,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Suppoſe many (if not moſt) of you are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready acquainted with the <hi>Providence</hi> which occaſioned theſe <hi>Papers</hi> I now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with: or, if any be ſtrangers thereto, they may be informed thereof from the <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> annexed. The <hi>Reverend Author</hi> whereof (ſufficiently known to divers of you both for his ability and integrity) hath thought fit to honour me ſo far, as to recommend the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it to me, together with this <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi> the ſubſtance whereof, on the ſame occaſion, was lately preached in the hearing of a conſiderable number of you.</p>
            <p>That I direct them to you eſpecially of this <hi>Neighbourhood,</hi> will be a ſufficient <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to After-times,</hi> that the matter of Fact to which they relate, is an undoubted Truth, ſeeing it dares in this manner to appear ſo open-faced before the whole Country where the Scene of it lay: and alſo a <hi>convictive Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> againſt all thoſe of you (if any ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:45297:5"/>there ſhall be) who after ſo loud a call to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and amendment of life, ſhall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in the practice of thoſe ſins for which the <hi>deceaſed young man</hi> (once your Neighbour) acknowledged to ſo many of his Viſitants, that the Divine Majeſty made him a ſpectacle to ſo many hundreds (I might ſay thouſands) for ſo many Months together.</p>
            <p>Wherefore my earneſt requeſt to you, is, that you will often recall to your memories that <hi>ſad ſtroke,</hi> which whilſt it was <hi>freſh News,</hi> ſo affected all the <hi>Spectators</hi> and <hi>Auditors</hi> thereof; that you may not loſe the good Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions then wrought in any of you. And to help you therein, when you find them wearing off, let <hi>this Book</hi> be your Monitor to renew and govern them; which was the end why it was publiſhed and directed to you eſpecially, by your <hi>Servant in the Goſpel,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45297:5"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PSAL. ix. 16. the former part.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>
                        <p>The Lord is known by the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which he executeth.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> that I ſhall make to you upon this <hi>Text,</hi> (as I ſuppoſe you will eaſily gheſs, if I ſhould not tell you) is occaſioned by as <hi>remarkable an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of <hi>Gods juſt Providence,</hi> (which moſt of you know to have lately faln out in our neighbourhood, and that ſo notoriouſly, as to fill all mens Tongues and Ears with the diſcourſe of it, and the Eyes of many hundreds, if not thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of them with the beholding it;) as it may be, in all the circumſtances, is <hi>hardly to be parallei'd in any Hiſtory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that which induced me to make ſuch a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe on this occaſion, was, <hi>partly,</hi> becauſe I thought it needful (at this convenient diſtance of Time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the common talk concerning it as News, is almoſt ſpent) to recall it again to your thoughts in a more ſerious and edifying way; leſt it ſhould die, as to its beſt uſe among you, as <hi>nine days wonders,</hi> (according to the Proverb) are wont to do? And <hi>partly,</hi> that (ſeeing the apprehenſions of men have been ſo different, and their diſcourſes ſo various about it, moſt men judging of it according to their particular Tempers and Humours, in compliance with the Principles they are governed by;) I might, ſo far as ſuch works of God, the main ſprings where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are concealed in his own breaſt, may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45297:6"/>by us, help you in ſome competent meaſure ſo to underſtand it, as to turn it to your greateſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and advantage: And <hi>laſtly,</hi> that having now gained the ſight of a juſt and impartial <hi>Narrative</hi> of that ſad Story from a <hi>Reverend Perſon</hi> of great Integrity, and a diligent enquirer into all the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances thereof, (to moſt of which he was an eye and ear-witneſs) I might diſpoſe you to receive it when it comes to <hi>publick view</hi> with more readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and give it the <hi>better entertainment,</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed before how to make uſe of it.</p>
                  <p>And the <hi>Text</hi> I have choſen for this purpoſe, is <hi>part</hi> of a <hi>Verſe</hi> made remarkable by <hi>two unuſual words</hi> in the cloſe of it; which, though Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters agree not in the expounding of them, yet they generally concur in this, that they have ſomething extraordinary in them, <hi>[viz. Higgaion, Selah.]</hi> For, whatever the <hi>latter</hi> may mean; or whether it be a bare <hi>Note</hi> in <hi>Muſick,</hi> which is an undetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned diſpute: the <hi>former</hi> of them, by the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the<note n="*" place="margin">Ab <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt ore; vel corde, medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt.</note> 
                     <hi>root</hi> whence it is derived, evidently recommends to us a matter of <hi>ſerious meditation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſuch indeed the <hi>Verſe</hi> is, being a ſolemn and weighty <hi>atteſtation</hi> of the holy <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> to the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence,</hi> upon occaſion of ſome remarkable appearance of it, on the behalf of his Church againſt ſome of their heathen Enemies; which is the ſubject of the preceding part of the <hi>Pſalm:</hi> the account whereof he ſeals up with this <hi>Epiphonemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Inſtruction</hi> to all the world, <hi>[The Lord is known by the Judgment which he executeth]</hi> and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by this oftentimes moſt remarkable circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance accompanying it, that he makes offenders themſelves the executioners thereof upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and <hi>enſnares them in the work of their own hands.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From the <hi>former part</hi> of which <hi>Divine Teſtimonial,</hi>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45297:6"/>(as I may properly call it) I intend, on this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to handle this <hi>plain obſervation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That Gods publick ſignal Judgments upon any offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or offenders are evident Teſtimonies by which he is known to mankind.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Doct.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the handling of which <hi>Obſervation,</hi> I ſhall endeavour theſe <hi>ſeven</hi> things:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. To ſhew you, what I mean, by theſe <hi>publick ſignal Judgments of God upon offenders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. To evince, by ſuch evidence, as I hope will be ſatisfactory to all rational men, that <hi>there are ſome ſuch penal ſtrokes</hi> inflicted by God on offenders in this life, as deſerve the name of <hi>ſignal Divine Judgments;</hi> and that ſuch events are not (as <hi>Atheiſts</hi> pretend) the meer products of <hi>chance,</hi> or <hi>caſualty.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. To prove, that <hi>God is</hi> (or ought to be) <hi>known by ſuch Judgments as theſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. To explain, <hi>what of God it is,</hi> which may be, and uſually is made <hi>known</hi> by them.</item>
                     <item>5. To give you the proper <hi>Characters,</hi> by which ſuch <hi>Divine Judgments</hi> are differenced from <hi>like Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences</hi> befalling men on other accounts.</item>
                     <item>6. To direct you in the <hi>application</hi> of ſuch <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to particular perſons and caſes, ſo as that you may not offend againſt <hi>Juſtice</hi> or <hi>Charity.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. And laſtly, to cloſe up this whole Diſcourſe with ſome <hi>uſeful practical Inferences.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> To ſhew you, <hi>[What I mean by theſe publick ſignal Judgments of God on offenders.]</hi> And here you are firſt to underſtand, that <hi>Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> in the notion of the Holy Scriptures, are of <hi>two ſorts,</hi> to wit,</p>
                  <p>His <hi>Judicia</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Judicantia,</hi> &amp;</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Judicata.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. His <hi>Judicia Judicantia;</hi> or <hi>Judgments pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced</hi> in the Sentence of his <hi>Law,</hi> dooming offenders to ſuch penalties for their offences againſt it. And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45297:7"/>it is uſual with the Scripture to call the <hi>Laws</hi> of God, on this account, <hi>his Judgments,</hi> and to joyn them with <hi>Statutes,</hi> as words of like import, as I could ſhew in very many places.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. His <hi>Judicia Judicata;</hi> or <hi>Judgments</hi> (in the phraſe of the Text) <hi>executed,</hi> which are the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer dooms actually inflicted; and are therefore called by the name of thoſe, according to which they do befall men. Now, though it be true, that no <hi>evil of ſuffering</hi> befalls any ſinner, but what (to ſpeak properly) is ſuch a <hi>Judgment of God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all evils penal are before denounced in Gods Law, which every ſinner breaks: yet the Scripture is not wont to call them all by that name. For that is uſually applyed to thoſe <hi>penal ſtrokes</hi> of God, which have ſome ſpecial Characters of his <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Juſtice</hi> upon them; to wit, ſomething in the <hi>nature</hi> of them, that is not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>common to men;</hi> or in the <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> ſomething of ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſuddenneſs from the unexpectedneſs or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likelyhood of their befalling men, in reſpect of the Time, Place, Condition, Imployment, Company, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or ſomething unuſual in the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> by which, or <hi>manner</hi> in which they are inflicted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and eſpecially, if there be any thing in them, that appears to be either <hi>above,</hi> or <hi>contrary</hi> to, or but <hi>beſides</hi> the wonted courſe of <hi>Nature,</hi> and ſo is either <hi>miraculous,</hi> or <hi>prodigious.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now theſe Two, are either inflicted on ſinners in a <hi>private</hi> way, ſo as few or none know of them, but ſuch as feel them, and thoſe who are intimately converſant with them: or elſe they are laid on them in a <hi>publick notorious manner,</hi> (as the Judgments amongſt us pronounced upon great offenders are wont to be executed) ſo as to call in, and invite Spectators to behold them. And ſuch <hi>Judgments,</hi> as theſe laſt, the Text muſt be meant of; and of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45297:7"/>ſuch I deſire to be underſtood, in what follows on this Argument.</p>
                  <p>And this ſhall ſuffice for my <hi>firſt</hi> undertaking.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. The <hi>ſecond</hi> deſerves to have more Time ſpent on it, becauſe it contains the <hi>main foundation</hi> of the whole following Diſcourſe. For, if there be <hi>no ſuch Judgments executed</hi> by God at all;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.11.</note> but <hi>Time and Chance,</hi> (in this caſe as well as others) not only <hi>happen to all,</hi> but <hi>govern all</hi> too: then there can be <hi>no knowledge</hi> of <hi>God</hi> drawn from them. Yea, if there be no ſuch things as <hi>Divine Judgments;</hi> then the very <hi>God</hi> they are ſuppoſed to atteſt to, (which is that the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> would have) may, for all their Teſtimony, <hi>not be.</hi> Whereas, if we evince by Reaſon, that <hi>any,</hi> though never ſo <hi>few,</hi> of thoſe Events, cannot be produced but by a Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; we do both prove the <hi>being</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> and withal vindicate Religion, from the imputation of being ſuperſtitious, in attributing <hi>all others</hi> of like nature to the <hi>ſame cauſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therefore on <hi>this Head,</hi> I take my ſelf to be obliged to make good theſe <hi>Two</hi> things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>That there are ſome penal Events which can by no rational Perſon be juſtly attributed to meer chance or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualty, or any like cauſe not capable of choice or deſign, in its actings.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>That ſuch penal Events, as theſe, muſt therefore be the effects of a Providence, and that Providence Divine.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">I. The <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe Propoſitions, I prove by the following Arguments.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. There are ſome <hi>penal Events</hi> befalling men in this world, which have been punctually <hi>threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> and <hi>foretold,</hi> as they have in the Iſſue faln out: and many of them ſo threatned and foretold in the very <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> with which they were accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied in the Event. As for inſtance,</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45297:8"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>(1.) In reference to the <hi>generality of Mankind.</hi> So in the <hi>firſt Threatning</hi> annexed to the Law given to our <hi>firſt Parents</hi> in Paradiſe;<note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> the daily experience of all Humane Nature, (taken notice of by <hi>Heathens</hi> themſelves) ſhews it to have been punctually ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, in the <hi>corruption</hi> and <hi>calamities</hi> generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falling the whole race of Men. And that other, in the Law given to <hi>Noah,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 9.6.</note> that <hi>whoſoever ſheds mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed;</hi> is continually (in the almoſt miraculous diſcoveries of <hi>Murders,</hi> and bringing Murderers to condign puniſhment) verified in the obſervation of the generality of Mankind to this very day. As alſo is that, of the wonderful ways by which <hi>Conſpiracies</hi> againſt <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Princes</hi> are brought to light, according to the notable threatning to that purpoſe, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.20.</item>
                     <item>(2.) And in reference to <hi>particular Perſons,</hi> and <hi>Nations.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">See, and compare Num. 20.12, 27, 28.24.27.12.15. Deut. 32.49.34.5.</note> So in the excluſion of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> from <hi>Canaan,</hi> it is taken notice of expreſly in the account given of their deaths, (of <hi>Aarons,</hi> by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> his own Brother, and of <hi>Moſes</hi> his own, by him that fills up his Story after his deceaſe) that it fell out to both of them according to what God had denounced. And it were eaſie to add many more of the ſame kind, to particular Perſons. But,<note place="margin">1 Kings 13.</note> that of the <hi>old Prophet</hi> to the <hi>diſobedient Prophet</hi> at <hi>Bethel;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Kings 7.19, 20.</note> that of <hi>Eliſha</hi> to the <hi>incredulous Lord in</hi> Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria; thoſe of <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>Micaiah</hi> to <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezebel,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Kings 21.19.23.22, 28.</note> ſhall ſuffice, inſtead of all the reſt, whereof the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical part of Scripture is full, becauſe they are ſo notoriouſly evident, to all that know the <hi>Bible.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And as to <hi>Nations.</hi> To omit the long Catalogue of all the <hi>plagues of Egypt,</hi> threatned and inflicted in the <hi>circumſtances</hi> mentioned in the relation of them: that one <hi>great Inſtance</hi> of the often foretold <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity</hi> of the whole <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation; is ſo obſervable, and ſo atteſted beyond all exception by the <hi>publick
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45297:8"/>Records</hi> of that Nation held to this day by all their Poſterity in veneration, that there is no more (nay not ſo much) cauſe to doubt it, then there is, that <hi>England</hi> was conquered by <hi>William the Norman.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhall cloſe this Argument with <hi>two Inſtances,</hi> ſo punctual in a circumſtance of all others moſt unlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be lighted on by chance; that I know not what can be objected againſt them to invalidate the force of them, but an Exception againſt the <hi>Records</hi> themſelves, whence they are taken: to which I ſhall therefore add a word or two anon.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>one,</hi> is that of the Judgment denounced againſt <hi>Jeroboams Altar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Kings 13.2.</note> and the Prieſts that offered on it, to be executed (as it was) by <hi>Joſiah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Kings 23.16.</note> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by his very Name, about 300 <hi>years</hi> before the performance.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>other,</hi> is that of the deſtruction of <hi>Babylon</hi> (in order to the reſtitution of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation;) wherein <hi>Cyrus</hi> is alſo, by his very Name,<note place="margin">Iſa. 44. ult. &amp; 45.1, 2.</note> foretold to be the Perſon that (as he did) was to effect it. Which Propheſie, by the learned <hi>Grotius</hi> his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, was uttered 170 <hi>years,</hi> and by that of <hi>Junius</hi> and others, above 200, before he accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed it, or probably was in being. And the very <hi>manner</hi> how he was to take that great Imperial City, (to wit, by the turning away and drying up <hi>Euphrates</hi>) is ſo lively deſcribed by the Prophet <hi>Jeremy;</hi> that the Heathen Authors, (<hi>Herodotus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jer. 50.38.51.31, 32.</note> and others) who give us an account of the event, juſtifie the verification of the prediction the ſame way.</p>
                  <p>Now in theſe and the like <hi>Predictions</hi> of future Events, with ſuch circumſtances, there is no man but muſt allow a greater <hi>certainty,</hi> (with reſpect to the <hi>cauſes</hi> on which they depend) then there can be in any products of <hi>meer Caſualty.</hi> Which is my <hi>firſt Argument.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45297:9"/>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>ſecond</hi> is this. There are <hi>Inſtances</hi> of ſome <hi>penal Events,</hi> that have been brought upon offenders in a way of <hi>formal Proceeding;</hi> yea, ſuch as is uſual even in <hi>Humane Judicatures.</hi> For In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. When <hi>Joſhua</hi> had forbidden the embezel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling any part of the ſpoil of <hi>Jericho</hi> under the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of a <hi>Divine Curſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joſh. 6.18.7 16, 17, 18.</note> 
                     <hi>Achan,</hi> the offender, falls under the danger of it: Upon the diſcomfiture of the Hoſt before <hi>Ai,</hi> enquiry is made after the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Tranſgreſſor of that Law. Then he is found out by the direction of a <hi>four-fold Lot,</hi> that brought all the people (down to his very family) under a ſcrutiny, till the Lot takes him. Then follows his Examination, Confeſſion, Judgment, and Execution. And not much unlike was the <hi>Proceſs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jon. 1.</note> by which <hi>Jonah</hi> was <hi>caſt into the Sea,</hi> and there impriſon'd in the <hi>belly</hi> of a <hi>Whale,</hi> till his Repentance procured his Releaſe. Now, abating the extraordinary way of diſcovery in theſe two caſes; the reſt of the <hi>Procedure</hi> in theſe Judgments in formed <hi>Methodically,</hi> according to the order of Humane Juſtice. And muſt theſe proceedings (in ſo exact a <hi>Method</hi> too) be attributed to meer <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualty?</hi> May not the perſons who have the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to aſſert this, as well affirm that Malefactors are <hi>hanged</hi> at <hi>Tyburn</hi> by meer <hi>Caſualty,</hi> when they have been ſeized by order of Law, committed to <hi>Newgate</hi> by warrant, tryed at the <hi>Seſſions-houſe,</hi> and having received their Sentence upon the Verdict of a Jury, been conducted to the place of Execution, and there turned off the Cart, by the known Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers thereunto by Law appointed?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. My <hi>third Argument</hi> is this. In the actual pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of offenders, many times the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> made uſe of have been <hi>irrational Creatures;</hi> and yet have by an <hi>unknown Influence</hi> been directed to act, as if they were governed by Principles of <hi>Juſtice,</hi>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:45297:9"/>as well as <hi>Reaſon:</hi> as putting an evident <hi>diſcrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>difference</hi> betwixt them and the innocent, when both of them have equally been within their Power. In the famous caſe of the plagues of <hi>Egypt,</hi> how came the <hi>Frogs,</hi> the <hi>Flies,</hi> the <hi>Hail,</hi> and the <hi>Plague,</hi> &amp;c. to ſeize only the Houſes, Cattle, bodies of <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and not touch an <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite,</hi> or any of his concerns, when (as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, by the <hi>order</hi> for the <hi>ſprinkling of the Jews houſes</hi> with the <hi>blood of the Paſchal Lamb</hi> for diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) they lived, for the moſt part,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.22.</note> and converſed intermixedly each with other? How was it, that the <hi>waters</hi> of the <hi>Red Sea ſtood as a wall</hi> on both ſides, whilſt the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were marching through it; and returned to their courſe,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> ſo ſoon as they came on dry land, to overwhelm <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and <hi>his Hoſt,</hi> who were in purſuit of them? When the <hi>three glorious Confeſſours</hi> were adjudged to the <hi>fiery Furnace</hi> by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> whence came it that the <hi>fire</hi> (ſo ragingly hot as it was) abſtained from <hi>touching</hi> ſo much as one <hi>hair of their heads,</hi> or <hi>ſinging</hi> their <hi>Garments,</hi> and to burn only their <hi>bonds</hi> aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſet them at liberty to <hi>walk</hi> in it,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.22. to 27.</note> who were caſt in <hi>bound:</hi> and yet to <hi>lick</hi> up and devour (even <hi>without</hi> the <hi>mouth of the Furnace</hi>) thoſe who <hi>caſt them in?</hi> And when <hi>Daniel</hi> himſelf was caſt into the <hi>Lions Den,</hi> and lodged among them in the <hi>bottom of the Den,</hi> one whole night, whence was it, that the hungry and cruel beaſts did not the <hi>leaſt hurt to him;</hi> and yet the very <hi>ſame Lions,</hi> when his <hi>Accuſers</hi> and their Relations were caſt in thither, <hi>had the maſtery of them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 6.22, 23, 24.</note> 
                     <hi>and brake all their bones in pieces, before they came to the bottom of the Den?</hi> Laſtly, (to name no more Examples of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) when the <hi>Lion,</hi> according to the prediction of the <hi>old Prophet</hi> at <hi>Bethel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Kings 13.</note> ſlew the <hi>Man of God</hi> that againſt Gods Commandment had <hi>eaten and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45297:10"/>drunk there;</hi> was he directed by meer <hi>chance</hi> ſo to do? Did he (being hungry, and ſeeking for Prey) light on him <hi>caſually</hi> only? If ſo, why (according to the uſual wont of ſuch beaſts of prey, as they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve who have been in thoſe Countries, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear falling on <hi>Men,</hi> but when they can light on no other food) did he not ſeize on his <hi>Aſs</hi> rather; but kill <hi>him,</hi> and not touch his <hi>Aſs,</hi> that (as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned in the danger) was afterwards found <hi>ſtanding by his ſide?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſe 28.</note> Why did he only kill him, and not <hi>devour</hi> him, and then withdraw to his Den: but rather chooſe to <hi>ſtand by him,</hi> as reſolved to avouch the fact: and that all the while the news was carrying to the City, and came by report to the old Prophet, and his Horſe ſadling, and he and his company travelling to the place of that ſad ſpectacle? And when they came, why did he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to carry away his prey ſo tamely as it ſeems he did? Do theſe things look like meer <hi>Caſualties?</hi> Is it not rather evident, that ſuch Agents acting ſo differently from their own nature and inclination, (ſo as to puniſh only the guilty, and ſingle them out among others equally within their reach) were directed by an <hi>Intelligent Cauſe,</hi> by whoſe order and Commiſſion they made this difference? And this is our <hi>ſecond</hi> Propoſition to be proved upon this Head; <hi>[That ſeeing theſe things cannot fall out by meer chance, or any thing elſe of like nature, they muſt be governed by Divine Providence]</hi> which I make good by theſe <hi>ſteps</hi> of <hi>rational Argumentation.</hi> Such E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents as fall not out by <hi>chance,</hi> fall out according to <hi>choice</hi> or <hi>contrivance.</hi> That choice and contrivance (in matter of puniſhment) muſt either be the choice and contrivance of the <hi>Sufferer</hi> or <hi>Inflicter. Sufferers</hi> are not wont to chooſe and contrive their own harms: but rather to avoid, and uſe what means they can to guard themſelves from them.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45297:10"/>If the <hi>Inflicter</hi> (then) chooſe and contrive the puniſhmenes mentioned; then, as the contrivance argues him to be a <hi>rational Being;</hi> ſo the bringing his contrivances to paſs by ſuch Inſtruments as have been mentioned, and with ſuch certainty, argues him to be ſuch a <hi>Being,</hi> as hath a <hi>predominant power</hi> over <hi>Nature</hi> it ſelf: which can be no other then <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine;</hi> and theſe effects mentioned, and the like, can be no other then the products of his <hi>Infinite Power</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> as you will ſee more anon.</p>
                  <p>Againſt the <hi>force</hi> of theſe <hi>Arguments,</hi> I cannot imagine how the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> can guard his Principles, but by excepting againſt the <hi>Evidence</hi> of the <hi>matter</hi> of <hi>fact</hi> in the Inſtances before mentioned: Seeing there is no clear proof of them, in moſt of the caſes, but from the <hi>H. Scriptures;</hi> which, though we own and reverence, yet he looks on with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and ſcorn, as not owning the <hi>Authority</hi> we allow them.</p>
                  <p>But he ought to conſider, that it is not in this whole proceſs of Argumentation in <hi>Queſtion</hi> before us, <hi>whether theſe writings be divinely inſpired or no?</hi> There is, herein, no other eſteem required to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, by him, but only what is due to <hi>credible Hiſtories.</hi> And it is enough for our preſent purpoſe, if they can juſtifie themſelves to be <hi>true Records</hi> of thoſe matters which fell out in thoſe Ages which they undertake to account for. And ſo much I can hardly imagine, how any man can have the forehead to deny: conſidering that they have all thoſe <hi>Motives</hi> of <hi>credibility</hi> for them, (with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of <hi>indiſputable Antiquity,</hi> and the having been <hi>owned</hi> by ſo great a part of the <hi>World</hi> for ſo many <hi>Ages</hi>) which <hi>other Hiſtories</hi> whatſoever can pretend to. Whence it muſt appear to all unbiaſſed Judges, that he that will allow (upon the Motives mentioned) <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and <hi>Thucydides,</hi> and <hi>Livy,</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:45297:11"/>and <hi>Tacitus,</hi> and other ſuch <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> to be compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent witneſſes of the matters of fact related by them; muſt needs be governed by prejudice rather then Reaſon, if he deny the ſame to <hi>Moſes</hi> and other Jewiſh Hiſtorians, concerning the matters falling out among them, who are, and have been always in greater eſteem in their own Nation, (who beſt knew their own ſtory) then thoſe mentioned ever were either in <hi>Greece</hi> or <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if yet (notwithſtanding all that hath been ſaid to the contrary) the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> will ſtill perſiſt in denying the <hi>matters of fact</hi> upon which the former Arguments are bottomed, becauſe they are (for the greateſt part) only recorded in <hi>that book,</hi> which it is the Intereſt of his Irreligion to disbelieve: What will he ſay to <hi>two Inſtances,</hi> (which I have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely reſerved to this place, becauſe they are ſo <hi>great,</hi> as to prove themſelves to be the effects of a Divine Providence;<note place="margin">Vid. H. Grot. Annot. ad libros ſuos de ver. Rel. Chr.</note> and becauſe they are confirmed by ſeveral <hi>Heathen</hi> Authors too, as well as related in the Holy Scripture) I mean the <hi>univerſal Deluge,</hi> and the deſtruction of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah?</hi> For if theſe Inſtances <hi>de facto</hi> be true; to which there is ſuch a concurring Evidence; he will find it very difficult to perſuade himſelf, (that I ſay not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) that ſo <hi>vaſt a quantity of waters</hi> as ſo covered all the face of the earth, and overflowed the <hi>higheſt Mountains,</hi> could be collected by any power leſs then <hi>Divine;</hi> and much leſs, come together by chance: and will be no leſs puzled, to ſhew by what inferior Agent ſuch a <hi>fire</hi> as burnt thoſe <hi>Cities</hi> could be kindled; and burn with that vehemence, as to preſerve its remembrance without altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in a <hi>Lake</hi> of ſulphurous water for ſo many thouſand years; (though that Lake continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for ſo long together hath ſwallowed all the Streams of ſo great a River as <hi>Jordan</hi> falling into
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45297:11"/>it) which is the conſtant wonder of all Travellers to this day.</p>
                  <p>And ſo I diſcharge my <hi>ſecond</hi> undertaking, to prove, <hi>[That there are ſome ſuch Judicial Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that have been executed by God.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. I come now to the <hi>third,</hi> to ſhew, <hi>[That God is, or ought to be, known by them]</hi> as he that works them upon that deſign. And here I ſhall be but brief, as indeed I need not to be large in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo plain and evident both from Reaſon and Scripture.
<list>
                        <item>For (1.) in <hi>Reaſon,</hi> what can be the end of Sovereign Providence in ſuch extraordinary ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances, but to manifeſt it ſelf and its Author? An end, for which even men are wont to do thoſe great things which at any time they have attained to, in publick Theaters, or other great concourſes of people, as our Saviours kindred tell him.</item>
                        <item>(2.) And the <hi>Scripture</hi> alſo declareth no leſs in other places.<note place="margin">Jo. 7.4.</note> So, when the Royal Pſalmiſt prophetically impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thoſe dreadful Judgments which make up the greateſt part of the 83. <hi>Pſalm;</hi> in the <hi>laſt</hi> Verſe he aſſigns the intended uſe of them to all the world; to wit, <hi>That men may know that he alone whoſe Name is</hi> Jehovah,<note place="margin">Pſal. 83. ult.</note> 
                           <hi>is the moſt High over all the Earth?</hi> And God himſelf is elſewhere brought in, upon the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations which he had made</hi> by his penal Providences <hi>in the Heathen world</hi> for oppreſſing his people, as calling on all men to <hi>behold thoſe his works, and be ſtill,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> to ceaſe from farther hoſtilities againſt his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts) as <hi>knowing</hi> by experience already dearly bought, that <hi>he is God,</hi> and (will they, nill they) reſolved to be ſo,<note place="margin">Pſal. 96.8, 9, 10.</note> and <hi>to be exalted in the earth.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>In a word, (to add no more Texts for proof of that which almoſt every Page in the Bible atteſts unto) the whole Church are by the Author of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalyps</hi> repreſented (upon ſuch notable Judicial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences) as <hi>ſinging the Song of</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Lamb,</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:45297:12"/>(<hi>i. e.</hi> a Chriſtian Song, like that of <hi>Moſes</hi> after the <hi>drowning of the Egyptians</hi>) and therein inſtructing all the world in this Duty.<note place="margin">Rev. 15.3, 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Who</hi> (ſay they) <hi>ſhall not fear thee, O Lord, and glorifie thy Name; for all Nations ſhall come and worſhip before thee, for thy Judgments are made manifeſt?</hi> Even as <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the <hi>Song</hi> to which this is parallel, infer from the Judgments of God on <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt, <hi>Who is like thee, O Lord, among the Gods? Who is like thee,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 15.11.</note> 
                     <hi>glorious in Holineſs, fearful in Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> (or the Actions whence thou gathereſt thy Praiſe) <hi>doing Wonders?</hi> And this opens the way to my <hi>ſourth</hi> Head.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. The Enquiry concerning <hi>[What of God it is, which is known or to be known by theſe ſignal Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And to this <hi>Enquiry</hi> I anſwer <hi>Two</hi> things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. His <hi>Being,</hi> and Exiſtence. <hi>[That there is a God.]</hi> For he that <hi>executeth Judgment</hi> ſo, as no finite li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited Being, no created Power can, muſt needs be a <hi>Supreme uncreated Being;</hi> that is, <hi>God.</hi> And this is an Argument ſo ſtrongly concluſive againſt the <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> that he is forced (to ſecure his Principles) to fly to that <hi>ſorry refuge of lyes,</hi> which I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore refuted; to buoy up his reputation among thoſe who know not the difference betwixt Reaſon and Noiſe, and judge no diſputant baffled, that hath any thing to ſay, though what he ſays be next to nothing. For, as he that is a meer <hi>ſtranger</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> if yet he ſee <hi>Courts of Judicature,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly kept in the <hi>Kings Name,</hi> and Criminals con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually puniſhed by a Power deputed and commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by him; cannot rationally doubt, <hi>whether there be a King in</hi> England: ſo neither can any man, with any colour of Reaſon; ſeeing Gods Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial Providences continually executing his known Laws, make it a Queſtion, <hi>Whether there be a God
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45297:12"/>that judgeth the Earth.</hi> Thus is <hi>Jehovah known by his Judgments,</hi> to <hi>be Jehovah.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. His eminent <hi>Divine Perfections</hi> and <hi>Glorious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes</hi> are illuſtriouſly manifeſted by his <hi>Judgments executed.</hi> As for Inſtance,
<list>
                           <item>(1.) His <hi>Juſtice;</hi> Which in theſe remarkable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences always juſtifies it ſelf; as ordinarily light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon thoſe offenders, concerning whom not only their own Conſciences, (as in the confeſſion of <hi>Pharaoh himſelf,</hi> crying out <hi>[The Lord is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and I and my people are wicked.]</hi> Exod. 9.27.) but alſo the whole world are, or may be, abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied they have <hi>deſerved</hi> it: yea, and among them, even they who not only <hi>commit thoſe crimes</hi> which they ſee puniſhed in others, but promote them, by <hi>ſhewing the pleaſure they take in thoſe that do them,</hi> yet <hi>know that they who do ſuch things are worthy of death;</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Rom. 1. ult.</note> and approve the Judgment of God, even in thoſe Sentences and Executions wherein they themſelves are implicitly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</item>
                           <item>(2.) His <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> In many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.
<list>
                                 <item>As 1. when he <hi>ſpares</hi> ſo <hi>many</hi> for every <hi>one</hi> that he ſmites, though equally criminal: and is as remarkable in his patience and long-ſuffering to ſome, as he is in his ſeverity to others.</item>
                                 <item>2. In <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing leſs then mens iniquities deſerve,</hi>
                                    <note place="margin">Ezra 9.13.</note> by how much the greateſt temporal ſuffering, that can be, is leſs than <hi>Hell.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3. In making the <hi>greateſt evils</hi> men ſuffer here, occaſions and means to preſerve them from <hi>greater Judgments</hi> hereafter.</item>
                                 <item>4. And <hi>laſtly,</hi> in making his ſeverities to the <hi>worſt</hi> of men the means of ſignal preſervations and deliverances to thoſe that are eminently good; and ſhewing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that he as well <hi>knows how to deliver the righteous,</hi>
                                    <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.9.</note> as to <hi>puniſh the wicked.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <pb n="16" facs="tcp:45297:13"/>
                           <item>(3.) His <hi>Omnipotent Power,</hi> and <hi>Sovereign Greatneſs,</hi> whilſt
<list>
                                 <item>[1.] he reacheth thoſe Malefactors that are too <hi>high</hi> for <hi>Humane Juſtice,</hi> and pride themſelves in their uncontrolableneſs by Humane Laws. Thus, by his dealing with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
                                    <note place="margin">Exod. 5.2.</note> who would own <hi>no Lord</hi> but himſelf, he draws an acknowledgement from <hi>Jethro,</hi> that <hi>he was greater than all Gods, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the thing wherein</hi> the proud Tyrant and his people <hi>dealt proudly,</hi>
                                    <note place="margin">Exod. 18.11.</note> 
                                    <hi>he was above them.</hi> And</item>
                                 <item>[2.] whilſt he ſummons in the <hi>poſſe</hi> of the <hi>whole Creation</hi> to bring ſuch <hi>over-ſized Malefactors</hi> to Execution, and arms the very meaneſt and moſt contemptible of them, (as <hi>flies,</hi> and <hi>lice,</hi> and <hi>frogs</hi>) with weapons to ſubdue and conquer them. And</item>
                                 <item>[3.] laſtly, whilſt he ſometimes makes a kind of <hi>new Creation,</hi> to ſerve his juſt ends, by altering the very courſe of Nature. as in the general deluge, when the very <hi>Fountains of the great Deep were broken up, i. e.</hi> The waters which were in the bowels of the Earth, with thoſe of the vaſt Ocean it ſelf, left their proper ſeat naturally ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for them, and <hi>came up to cover the face of the Earth.</hi>
                                    <note place="margin">Gen. 7.11.</note>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>(4.) His <hi>Verity</hi> or <hi>Truth;</hi> Often, in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of <hi>particular</hi> threatnings and predictions in particular caſes, as thoſe before mentioned: and always, (even in them too) in fulfilling the <hi>general Curſes</hi> and denunciations of his wrath againſt the Tranſgreſſors of his Laws. So that men are hereby convinced, that his <hi>Judgments</hi> are not only <hi>righteous,</hi> but <hi>true.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Apoc. 15.3.16.7.19.2.</note>
                           </item>
                           <item>(5.) His <hi>Omniſcience,</hi> or certain knowledge of all the Words and Actions of men, though never ſo much concealed in all imaginable ſecreſie: and yet oftentimes by the proceſs of his Judicial Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he brings them to light.
<list>
                                 <item>For (1.) by them he ſometimes draws out of the boſoms of offenders, by their <hi>own Confeſſion,</hi> (as in the caſes of <hi>Achan,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45297:13"/>Jonah,</hi> and others) thoſe things which were not otherwiſe diſcoverable. And</item>
                                 <item>(2.) by ſtrange and unuſual accidents he ſets the <hi>inquiſitive humor</hi> of men on work, to lay <hi>odd</hi> and <hi>uncouth paſſages</hi> and circumſtances together, till at laſt they make a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient <hi>concurrent Evidence,</hi> to convict Malefactors of ſecret and unknown Crimes; than which there is nothing more uſual in ordinary <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Juſtice.</hi> So that it comes frequently to paſs, as <hi>Zophar</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, that <hi>the Heavens firſt reveal mens iniquities,</hi>
                                    <note place="margin">Job 20.27.</note> 
                                    <hi>and then the earth riſes up againſt them.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>(6.) And <hi>laſtly,</hi> (not to multiply more particulars on this Head) his <hi>Infinite Wiſdom,</hi> and moſt <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Counſel;</hi> whereby he manageth thoſe penal Providences ſo, as to out-wit the wiſeſt of men, when they imploy all their Policy to ſecure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: by which he ſhews himſelf <hi>wonderful in Counſel,</hi> and gives the world daily occaſion <hi>wiſely to conſider his doings,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Pſal. 64.9.</note> to find out the admirable contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the wheels and ſprings, by which that great Engine is moved, which <hi>takes the wiſe in their own craftineſs,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Job 5.13.</note> and <hi>ſnares the wicked</hi> (as the following part of my Text expreſſeth it) <hi>in the work of their own hands.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And in many of thoſe great works, when Ages have ſtudied them all they can, yet ſtill there is ſomething remaining undiſcoverable to exerciſe the wonder of the moſt curious Enquirers, and make them cry out with the holy Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.33.</note> 
                     <hi>O the depth! How unſearchable are Gods Judgments, and his ways paſt finding out!</hi> And this ſhall ſuffice to be ſpoken to my <hi>fourth</hi> Head.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. The <hi>fifth</hi> follows, to wit, To give you the beſt account I can, of <hi>[The diſtinguiſhing Characters by which ſuch Divine Judgments are differenced from like Providence befalling men upon other Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:45297:14"/>
                  <p>The reaſon of which diſquiſition is, becauſe God many times either actively inflicts, or (at leaſt) paſſively permits <hi>great</hi> afflicting <hi>evils,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall men, yea, the <hi>beſt men;</hi> which are not to be ranked by us under this Head of <hi>Judicial Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> as being intended by God to promote holy Deſigns of his own of quite a different Nature, and tendency.</p>
                  <p>Now in the purſuance of this <hi>great Enquiry,</hi> I ſhall <hi>firſt</hi> adventure to your conſideration ſome <hi>general obſervations concerning Divine Judgments,</hi> which may conduce to the governing our ſelves in it with due caution: and then give you the <hi>Characters</hi> I promiſed.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>general obſervations</hi> are theſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">[1.] That ſuch <hi>publick ſignal Judgments</hi> as my Text and Doctrine ſuppoſe, are a ſort of Divine Providences which God doth more <hi>rarely</hi> than is ordinarily believed, exhibit to the world. For he himſelf calls the execution of Judgment in ſuch publick and notorious manner,<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.21.</note> 
                     <hi>his ſtrange work.</hi> And (ſpeaking after the manner of men) tells us,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.33.</note> 'tis that which he <hi>doth not willingly, i. e.</hi> not of his own natural propenſion, but upon the urgency of ſome ſpecial occaſions, which indiſpenſably require it. Wherefore it is, that the obliging Inſtances of his Mercy and Bounty, his Patience and long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and other expreſſions of his <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> (his moſt natural Attribute) are the <hi>daily</hi> and <hi>hourly</hi> exerciſe of his Providence: but thoſe other harſh aad unwelcome Iſſues of it (like <hi>unnatural Births</hi>) are produced but now and then. And that
<list>
                        <item>(1.) <hi>partly,</hi> becauſe this world is not properly <hi>ſeculum Mercedis,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Rom. 2.9.</note> the ſeaſon for the <hi>revelation of the righteous Judgment of God, wherein to render to every man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his works;</hi> but that buſineſs is reſerved for the world to come, and the <hi>Day in which he hath
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45297:14"/>appointed to judge the world by the man whom he hath ordained:</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Acts 17.31.</note> and he thinks it (therefore) not fit to leſſen the expectation thereof, by a ſeeming <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation</hi> of the imployment proper thereunto: and</item>
                        <item>(2.) <hi>partly,</hi> becauſe he is deſirous to keep up the juſt <hi>value</hi> of ſuch great occurrences by the <hi>rarity</hi> of them; which if they were common, would grow into like diſeſteem with other things that come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der daily obſervation: and</item>
                        <item>(3.) <hi>partly,</hi> becauſe, as a <hi>bountiful Benefactor,</hi> he is not willing to ſtreigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his liberality to the very worſt of men; but to give them a plentiful ſhare of the <hi>good things</hi> of this life, whoſe <hi>portion</hi> is laid out <hi>here:</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Luke 16.25.</note> And <hi>laſtly,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Pſal. 17.14.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it conduceth to the <hi>glory</hi> of his <hi>Juſtice</hi> in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, to give bad men (of themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to grow inſolent upon his forbearance) the occaſion of <hi>hardening their hearts in evil,</hi> by not <hi>executing Sentence againſt every wicked work ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.11.</note>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">[2.] That it is highly probable, that theſe ſorts of unuſual Providences are yet <hi>rarer</hi> in the <hi>latter Ages</hi> of the world, than in the <hi>earlier:</hi> and under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and among <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> then under the <hi>Law,</hi> and among the <hi>Jews.</hi> Becauſe there was in thoſe times more occaſion for them, and uſe of them, than now there is. Before the <hi>Scripture</hi> in any part was written, <hi>Tradition,</hi> with the reliques of the <hi>light of Nature,</hi> ſometimes aſſiſted with <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Revelation,</hi> was the <hi>Rule</hi> whereby the world was governed. But becauſe the <hi>two former</hi> were much corrupted, and the <hi>third</hi> afforded but now and then to a few eminently good men; the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality had need to be often taught their Duty, as Gedeon <hi>taught the men of</hi> Succoth <hi>with thorns and briars,</hi> ſharp and ſevere Providences.<note place="margin">Judges 8.16.</note> And even after ſo much of it was written, as ſerved to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the <hi>Jewiſh Church</hi> under that Adminiſtration,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45297:15"/>God was pleaſed to keep up ſtill, in great part, the ſame Method of adminiſtring his Kingdom upon earth by exemplary Providences. As (probably) conſidering,
<list>
                        <item>(1.) that what was ſo written, was to be kept among them to whom it did principally <hi>pertain;</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Rom. 9.4.</note> and that the reſt of the world was to be left generally in the ſame condition they were in before. And</item>
                        <item>(2.) that (by the difference put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Jews</hi> and them, by a peculiar <hi>diſcrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Religion</hi>) the reſt of the world were generally like to be exaſperated againſt them; ſo, that had they not been kept in awe by ſuch penal Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces now and then, they would continually have been attempting the extirpation of a ſort of men ſo odious: and had not the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in their <hi>ſingular Religion,</hi> by ſuch frequent miraculous appearances of God for the puniſhment of their perſecutors, they would have been the more tempted to have purchaſed their peace with their Neighbours, by waving their Religious obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to purchaſe their good will. And</item>
                        <item>(3.) that this Law, to the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, was for the moſt part <hi>like a book ſealed;</hi> in that the greateſt encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements to obedience, (the great <hi>Promiſes</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi>) were obſcured under dark expreſſions, and typical ſhadows,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.14.</note> till the <hi>vail on</hi> Moſes <hi>his face was taken away by Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>life and immortality by him were brought to light:</hi>
                           <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.10.</note> and therefore even they had ſtill much need to be quickned to their duty by ſenſible Motives, And</item>
                        <item>(4.) <hi>laſtly,</hi> that they were, by the very conſtitution and temper of the Nation, a very <hi>ſtiff-necked</hi> and unmanageable People; and ſo not eaſily to be kept in obedience by bare <hi>written Rules,</hi> without a <hi>Rod</hi> of ſevere <hi>Temporal Judgments,</hi> frequently laid on the backs of ſome amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to keep the reſt in awe.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:45297:15"/>
                  <p>And if we alſo conſider theſe Particulars, (as God probably did) and ſome others that might be ſuggeſted of the like nature; we may very well (I think) be ſatisfied, that if we do <hi>not now hear</hi> of ſuch <hi>frequent notorious Executions</hi> of Divine Juſtice as then were the <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> ſince <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that Church ſpread over all the world; the <hi>clearneſs</hi> and <hi>perſpicuity</hi> of his Doctrine in the main induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to a good life; and the more plentiful effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>the Holy Spirit upon all fleſh</hi> to produce a more filial obedience thereunto; render it leſs neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that we <hi>ſhould do ſo:</hi> Eſpecially, ſeeing we have all thoſe great Inſtances of Divine ſeverity which were exhibited in thoſe ancient Ages, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered down even to us <hi>upon whom the ends of the world are come,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.11.</note> by holy Pen-men in writing, <hi>for our admonition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">[3.] That the <hi>certain Interpretation</hi> of ſuch rare Judicial Providences, when they now adays fall out, is to us in theſe latter Times more <hi>difficult,</hi> that it was to the men of thoſe days, in which they were more frequent. The Reaſon whereof is, becauſe God, ſince the <hi>Scriptures</hi> were compleated, and generally received, hath put a <hi>ſtop</hi> to that <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Propheſie,</hi> which in former Times raiſed up Prophetical Men, to predict and threaten Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments before they came, and interpret them infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly when they came. So that the moſt perfect Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we can now make of them, though we uſe all the means left us to that purpoſe with the greateſt and moſt conſcientious exactneſs, will fall very ſhort of <hi>Infallibility,</hi> and amount, at moſt, only to a great <hi>Moral certainty,</hi> in moſt caſes of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                  <p n="4">[4.] That it is therefore very <hi>eaſie</hi> to <hi>miſtake</hi> in this affair, and be deceived by the making ſuch <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations</hi> of Divine Providences of this nature
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45297:16"/>as <hi>Phancy</hi> and <hi>Paſſion,</hi> (continually ready herein to interpoſe) may be apt to ſuggeſt to us: and the moſt of men (and too many good men too) are very prone to be miſled by them themſelves, and to miſlead others.</p>
                  <p n="5">[5.] That ſuch errours and miſtakes, are not more <hi>eaſie</hi> and <hi>frequent,</hi> than (as they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly made uſe of) <hi>ſinful</hi> and <hi>dangerous.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, by our aptneſs to avouch them, and (in a ſort) impoſe them on the belief of others, we too often render our ſelves guilty of <hi>prophaning Gods Name,</hi> (of which his great works are a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part) by ſtamping our own fond conceits with his <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Superſcription,</hi> which is no leſs a crime in this caſe <hi>againſt God,</hi> than the minting and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding adulterate Coin in worldly dealings and payments is to the <hi>temporal Prince,</hi> under whom we live.</p>
                  <p n="6">[6.] And yet, <hi>laſtly,</hi> (notwithſtanding all that hath been ſaid to beget a new caution in us in a matter of ſo great an import) I muſt avouch, that I do not believe God hath <hi>altogether tyed up his hands</hi> from executing ſignal Judgments, even in <hi>theſe days,</hi> or in thoſe Regions where the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with greateſt clearneſs and moſt powerful Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: Eſpecially, in caſe the <hi>ſubſtantial corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions</hi> of ſo pure a Religion be at any time ſo groſs, or the general <hi>debauchery</hi> of mens lives under ſuch excellent Inſtructions be ſo foul and ſcandalous to the holy Doctrine of our Saviour, as to call for them: and when any new <hi>Impieties</hi> of the largeſt dimenſions, and prodigious <hi>Immoralities,</hi> become bold and audacious beyond the examples of the former Ages of Chriſtianity, (with impunity, if not countenance and encouragement, from thoſe that ought to ſuppreſs them) among thoſe that are the noted Profeſſors of it. Nor do I think that we
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45297:16"/>are, in ſuch caſes, ſo deſtitute of direction, <hi>partly,</hi> from parallel Inſtances of Scripture; and <hi>partly,</hi> from the general motions of Mankind in all Ages concerning ſuch Providences; and <hi>partly,</hi> from the concurring Evidence of the circumſtances of them when they ſo fall out, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but that we may, even in theſe days, by the <hi>ordinary aſſiſtance</hi> of Gods <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> (even without a Revelation) diſcern ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient marks and tokens of Divine Judgments upon many of them, to lay a foundation for the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them to the ends which God generally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns by them, both to our ſelves and others. For a <hi>moral certainty,</hi> in ſuch matters wherein a Duty is to be inferred from the various accidents of this life, hath (to us) the force of a <hi>Divine Command.</hi> A Principle, which if it be not owned, we muſt neceſſarily be endangered to be governed, in moſt of the ordinary actions of our preſent callings and imployments, by that <hi>wild</hi> and <hi>extravagant Rule</hi> of <hi>exſpecting ſpecial Scripture-determinations</hi> in all the particularities of our worldly conditions; which no ſober man will own as the meaſure to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern his Actions by.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And ſuch (in the <hi>ſecond</hi> place) as I have deſcribed, I hope, will the <hi>characters</hi> of remarkable Divine Judgments be, that follow.</p>
                  <p n="1">(1.) The <hi>greatneſs</hi> and <hi>publickneſs</hi> of a Divine ſtroke, beyond what is <hi>common to men;</hi> eſpecially, if ſo great, as in common repute to be above the power of man to inflict, (as I have before intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) gives the firſt glimpſe of light in this Caſe. Which puts us, (as it lawfully may, nay, more in duty ought where the concern is ſome way our own) upon enquiry into the <hi>Nature</hi> of it. For we are wonted to do ſo in Humane Societies. If a <hi>ſtranger</hi> come by a <hi>Gallows</hi> or a <hi>Whipping-poſt,</hi> and ſee a man <hi>hanged,</hi> and <hi>drawn,</hi> and <hi>quartered</hi> at the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45297:17"/>
                     <hi>one,</hi> and another ſeverely <hi>whipped</hi> at the other; he will preſently be enquiring, wherefore ſuch perſons are handled with ſuch ſeverity in ſo notorious a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner? And when ſeverities, it may be far greater from God, befall any with as publick circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, it is equally rational for the <hi>ſpectators,</hi> and much more the <hi>ſufferers,</hi> to enquire what he means by them; and even to ſuſpect the worſt, that they may be <hi>Judicial Executions,</hi> till he be informed otherwiſe. Yea, God himſelf intimates his appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of mens inquiſitiveneſs, in ſuch caſes: when he tells the <hi>Jews,</hi> that he would inflict ſuch ſore plagues on them, as ſhould move all Nations to ask, <hi>Wherefore hath the Lord done thus unto this Land?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 29.24.</note> 
                     <hi>What meaneth the heat of this great Anger?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) But this alone, is not a <hi>ſufficient character</hi> to warrant us to pronounce ſuch a ſtroke to be a <hi>Divine Judgment,</hi> how ſevere ſoever it be; except there appear as evident and notorious <hi>a crime</hi> in conjunction with it. For the judging by the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer mark</hi> ſingly, miſled <hi>Jobs</hi> friends in his Caſe: and the men of <hi>Melita</hi> in the cenſure they paſſed upon St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 28.4.</note> when they ſaw the <hi>Viper hanging on his hand.</hi> And it may miſlead us in like caſes. For if we interpret all ſuch great and remarkable ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, on whomſoever they fall, to be Divine Judgments, we ſhall be often endangered unjuſtly to <hi>condemn the Generation of Gods beſt Children.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.15.</note> But where <hi>both</hi> theſe in the ſame perſons meet, with equal Evidence; we can hardly be miſtaken, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept all Mankind be ſuppoſed to be ſo too, who commonly argue in ſuch caſes from this character) in calling ſuch Providences <hi>Judgments of God:</hi> or, if we be miſtaken, it is (in a ſort) a ſafe errour; as that which (if we make a religious uſe of our apprehenſions about it) will miſlead us only
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45297:17"/>into ſuch affections and actions as tend to Gods glory, and our own benefit and advantage.</p>
                  <p n="3">(3.) And a far greater evidence is given in this Caſe many times, to make <hi>Divine Judgments ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt,</hi> by the fair and legible <hi>Impreſſion</hi> and <hi>Image</hi> of the very offence it ſelf, upon the puniſhment in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted.<note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> The <hi>drowning of</hi> Pharaoh <hi>and the</hi> Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> was a puniſhment ſo like their ſin in <hi>drowning all the male Children of the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>in the River:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 1.20. Levi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 10.1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> the burning <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> with a <hi>ſtrange fire from Heaven,</hi> was a Divine ſtroke ſo aptly ſuted to their offence in offering Incenſe with <hi>ſtrange fire to Heaven:</hi> the inceſtuous defilement of <hi>Davids Concubines</hi> by <hi>Abſalom,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.11.</note> had ſo expreſs a ſignature of the defilement of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riahs wife</hi> by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid:</hi> and (to mention no more Examples at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) the <hi>cutting off the Thumbs and great Toes of</hi> Adonibezek himſelf,<note place="margin">Judges 1.7.</note> was ſo ſignal a requital of the like cruelty ſhewed by him to 70 <hi>Kings</hi> before: that no man needs to doubt the lawfulneſs of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them by the Name they have always born, that of remarkable Divine Judgments. And it can rationally be no matter of ſcruple to any one, to give Providences of the like ſtamp the ſame name ſtill.</p>
                  <p n="4">(4.) And it makes much to the ſtrengthning the Evidence in ſuch matters, when ſuch <hi>remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Divine ſtrokes tread cloſe</hi> upon the <hi>heels of ſome notorious offence,</hi> as oftentimes they do: yea, ſo cloſe, as to ſurpriſe the offender in the very Act.<note place="margin">Gen. 19.11.</note> The ſtriking the <hi>Sodomites blind</hi> in the very attempt of a foul ſin not to be named; and the firing of the whole <hi>City</hi> the next morning with a ſtorm of flaming Brimſtone;<note place="margin">Num. 16.32.</note> the <hi>cleaving of the Earth to</hi> ſwallow <hi>Korah</hi> and his company, even whilſt they ſtood daringly in the face of God and the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, to avouch a foul Rebellion againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:45297:18"/>and a ſacrilegious uſurpation of <hi>Aarons Prieſthood;</hi> the <hi>running through of</hi> Zimri <hi>and</hi> Cosbi,<note place="margin">Num. 25.8.</note> in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry act of bold and audacious uncleanneſs; the <hi>ſlaying</hi> of <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> the <hi>very night</hi> following his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane debauch, acted by the abuſe of <hi>Gods Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Veſſels</hi> to <hi>drunkenneſs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 5.30.</note> at an Idols feaſt; the turning of his Grandfather <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> a-gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing among oxen, when that vaunting brag was ſcarce out of his mouth,<note place="margin">Dan. 4.31, 32, 33.</note> 
                     <hi>Is not this great</hi> Babylon <hi>that I have built for the houſe of the Kingdom, by the might of my power?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 5.5, 10.12.22, 23.</note> the ſmiting <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> dead, with a lye in their mouths to cover their ſacrilege; the <hi>eating up Herod</hi> by <hi>worms,</hi> ſo cloſely attending upon his owning the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous flattery of the people: and many more like Inſtances to theſe, none ever gave a <hi>ſofter Title</hi> to, than that of <hi>Divine Judgments.</hi> And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>drunkards</hi> breaking his neck in his drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, and the hectoring <hi>challengers</hi> being ſlain in a Duel, and the <hi>perjured</hi> perſons being ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten dumb or dead in his perjury, and the like penal events befalling other ſinners in the very act of other ſins of as hainous a nature; may not ſtill, by a parity of Reaſon, paſs for Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſame denomination, I cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine.</p>
                  <p n="5">(5.) When ſuch <hi>penal Providences</hi> are the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and notorious conſequents of provoking and daring <hi>Appeals, Applications,</hi> or <hi>Addreſſes to God</hi> of any kind; or of <hi>conteſts with him:</hi> there is all the Reaſon in the world why we ſhould take them for <hi>Divine Judgments,</hi> extorted by an impious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, or provoking Inſolence.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1.) In caſe of <hi>Appeals</hi> to God, <hi>implicit</hi> or <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit.</hi> When the <hi>bitter water,</hi> under the Law, envenomed by the imprecation of the diſloyal wife againſt her ſelf, in caſe ſhe was guilty of the fact
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45297:18"/>ſhe was ſuſpected of, <hi>cauſed her belly to ſwell, and her thigh to rot;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Num. 5.22.</note> the implicit <hi>Appeal</hi> to Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion in this caſe, made the event evidently to be a Divine Judgment. When <hi>Korah</hi> and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices dare put it to a Divine determination,<note place="margin">Num. 16.5.</note> 
                        <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had not as much right to offer Incenſe as</hi> Aaron <hi>and his Sons:</hi> The Event in this Caſe declared that God judged the cauſe in which he was thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to againſt them? And when the wicked <hi>Jews</hi> by tumultuous out-cries call on <hi>Pilate</hi> to <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie Jeſus</hi> for a <hi>Malefactor,</hi> and encourage him, when his Conſcience boggles at ſo foul an act of Injuſtice, with this fearful imprecation, (in the nature of ſuch an <hi>Appeal</hi>) that if he were not guilty, God would lay <hi>his blood on them and their children;</hi> and the Event of ſo many Ages hath declared the ſaid guilt not to be yet waſhed off from their whole Poſterity: None but an <hi>hardened Jew</hi> will ever doubt, whether there be a <hi>Divine Judgment</hi> in this caſe or no. Laſtly, When holy <hi>Job</hi> (againſt the unjuſt charges of his cenſorious friends, who among other crimes, taxed him with <hi>breaking the arms of the fatherleſs:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Job 22.9.</note> 
                        <hi>i. e.</hi> That by his power he had ſo cruſhed them that they were diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to maintain their right againſt him) had appeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to God for his vindication, and imprecated againſt himſelf, that if he were guilty of this Crime, <hi>his Arm might fall from his Shoulder-blade,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Job 31.21, 22.</note> 
                        <hi>and be broken from the bone; i. e.</hi> That the fleſh might rot from the bone, till his Arm fell from his Shoulder; if a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after, that <hi>Arm had dropped off</hi> according to ☜ his Execration, and ſome concurring evidence withal had appeared to prove him guilty of the fact which he ſo diſclaimed, (I ſay, if it had ſo faln out, which it did not, becauſe he was innocent) had not his friends been juſtified, if they had cryed out in the words of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45297:19"/>
                        <hi>Behold! the Lord is known by the Judgment that he executeth!</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2.) In caſe of <hi>Addreſs</hi> or <hi>Application</hi> to him, in matters of another nature. As in <hi>promiſſory Oaths,</hi> (or which in ſubſtance is all one) <hi>Imprecations</hi> of Gods vengeance, upon <hi>non-performance</hi> of what men undertake to do. Which <hi>Addreſſes</hi> are either <hi>ſerious</hi> or <hi>cuſtomary.</hi> And in both ſorts, <hi>Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> may be manifeſted, as the circumſtances may be.
<list>
                           <item>(1.) In <hi>ſerious addreſſes</hi> of this kind. As in the Caſe of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they were obliged to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to the <hi>fearful Curſes</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Law;<note place="margin">Deut. 29. from 15. to 26.</note> they did therein implicitly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs themſelves to God, and pray, that all thoſe curſes, in caſe of diſobedience to that Law, might befall them; which Curſes are therefore called the <hi>Curſes of the Covenant,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Deut. 29.21.</note> becauſe they covenanted with God upon that penalty to keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments there mentioned. And therefore, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when God had executed thoſe ſeverities upon them, which made all the Neighbour-Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to enquire, <hi>[Wherefore the Lord had dealt ſo with them.]</hi> Men are directed by God to anſwer, <hi>Becauſe they have forſaken the Covenant of the Lord,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Ver. 25. to 29.</note> 
                              <hi>the anger of the Lord was kindled againſt this Land to bring upon it all the curſes written in this Book.</hi> And he moreover tells them, that they need not fear offending by a <hi>raſh cenſure,</hi> where Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with the Cauſes of them were ſo manifeſt. For <hi>though ſecret things belong to God; i. e.</hi> in dark caſes, we muſt not be too forward to paſs our ſentence upon Gods providential proceedings; yet <hi>things revealed,</hi> (as ſuch <hi>Judgments</hi> inflicted upon ſuch a <hi>forfeiture</hi> by Covenant betwixt God and a People are) <hi>belong to us and our children,</hi> to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret and improve them. And the like may be the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45297:19"/>caſe of <hi>particular perſons,</hi> when they vow and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly Covenant with God to leave ſuch vices, and amend their lives; and to bind themſelves the more firmly, imprecate ſuch evils upon themſelves, in caſe they fail in performance. Of which there is a notable Inſtance in one of our late Writers, of Sir <hi>Jervaſe Ellowis,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Wilſon</hi> Hiſt. of K. <hi>James.</hi>
                              </note> (as he calls him) who at the place of Execution took notice to all the people pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of <hi>Gods juſt Judgment</hi> that brought him to that <hi>end:</hi> for that he had ſolemnly (being given to <hi>gaming</hi>) upon ſome ſpecial occaſion, prayed to God, <hi>That if he did ſo any more, be might be hang'd: and having broken promiſe with God, he had brought his own wiſh upon him.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>(2.) In <hi>cuſtomary Addreſſes</hi> of that nature; when men upon every ſlight occaſion imprecate in the form of a <hi>cuſtomary wiſh,</hi> (as a vain <hi>Parentheſis</hi> in diſcourſe, with ſome perſons too frequent) any evil upon themſelves, to back every ſlight purpoſe or trivial Promiſe that drops unadviſedly from their lips: Theſe men, though they uſe not Gods Name explicitly in ſuch forms of diſcourſe, (and yet too often even that is done, [<hi>I wiſh to God,</hi> &amp;c.] is too frequent a Phraſe) yet they do imply it, and it hath the force of an application to God, to inflict ſuch an evil on them. Now, if when men fail, as too often they do, in thoſe unadviſed promiſes of theirs, and God brings the calamity they wiſhed upon them; I ſhould not ſcruple in ſuch a caſe to look on it as the execution of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Judgment, to warn people, how they uſe any expreſſions wherein <hi>Gods Name</hi> is concerned, in a <hi>ſlight</hi> and <hi>cuſtomary</hi> manner. And I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, if it were well obſerved, God doth to very many perſons of lewd Tongues, perform in earneſt, what they ſo often inconſiderately impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate in this world: and doubt the doth ſo to many
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45297:20"/>more in another world, where their <hi>[God-damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me's]</hi> and <hi>[The-Devil-take-me's]</hi> and the like familiar forms of cuſtomary diſcourſe, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane men, are (with the ſtinging atteſtations of their own Conſciences to Gods Juſtice therein) ſadly verified upon them to all eternity.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>3.) In caſe of <hi>Conteſts with God, Gods Judgments</hi> are often <hi>manifeſted</hi> and made known to be what indeed they are. As,
<list>
                           <item>(1.) When they light upon the <hi>furious main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers</hi> of a <hi>falſe Religion</hi> againſt the <hi>true:</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, if in a publick and notorious <hi>competition,</hi> God be (as it were) <hi>challenged</hi> to appear in the vindication of his Truth. Which was the caſe of <hi>Baals Prieſts</hi> in their notable conteſt with <hi>Elijah,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God brought them to publique Execution,<note place="margin">1 Kings 18.</note> by a miraculous Confutation in the preſence of all Iſrael.</item>
                           <item>(2.) When ſuch <hi>Divine ſeverities</hi> befall the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours and propugners of <hi>Atheiſm and Irreligion,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>all Religion.</hi> If ſuch perſons <hi>die not the common death of other men,</hi> the common vote of Mankind pronounceth them to be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a <hi>Divine Judgment.</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Vid. Cic. de N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>t. Deor m. I. 1, &amp; 2. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ert in vit. Prot. Ariſtip. Epic. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>nis. Athen. I. 13. Aelian. I. 4.</note> As appears, by the cenſures paſſed by Heathens, themſelves upon the ſtrange ends of <hi>Diagoras, Protagoras, Bion, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus, Epicurus, Pherecides,</hi> and others, who ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were, or were generally reputed, <hi>Atheiſts</hi> among them: And by thoſe of the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures on <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> and of the Eccleſiaſtical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters on <hi>Caligula, Maximinus, Julian,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Atheiſtical and prophane promoters of Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</item>
                           <item>(3.) When the like ſevere Providences befall ſuch, as though they profeſs the <hi>true Religion,</hi> yet becauſe they make uſe of that Profeſſion only as a <hi>mask,</hi> to cover thoſe deſigns againſt it, (which they dare not carry on with open face) God
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45297:20"/>fore-dooms in the Scripture (as guilty of moſt pernicious oppoſition againſt it) to a notable and ſignal Ruine and Deſtruction. As in the caſe of the <hi>great Antichriſt;</hi> when God, having <hi>revealed that wicked one fully,</hi> ſhall finally deſtroy both him, and his Seat, where <hi>ſitting in the Temple of God,</hi> he acts the <hi>Devil</hi> in <hi>Gods Name,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.4. to 12.</note> by <hi>Satanical ſigns and lying wonders:</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Apoc. 15.2, 3, 4, 19.1, 2.</note> both the Church Militant and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant are called on to acknowledge and <hi>rejoyce</hi> in the <hi>juſt Judgments</hi> of God executed on him and his Adherents.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="6">(6. It is no ſlight Evidence to a <hi>Divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> when (as it often falls out) an <hi>offenders Conſcience</hi> under ſuch a remarkable ſtroke of Gods Hand, <hi>owns</hi> it as the juſt puniſhment of ſuch a particular noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Crime: and <hi>gives glory to God,</hi> (with <hi>Achan</hi>) by confeſſing it before the world. When <hi>Adonibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek,</hi> convicted by his own Conſcience, cryes out,<note place="margin">Jud. 1.7.</note> 
                     <hi>as I have done, ſo hath God</hi> requited me: and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs Brethren,</hi> in the danger they were in to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for <hi>Spies</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> charge themſelves with the guilt of their envy and cruelty againſt their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;<note place="margin">Gen. 42.21.</note> and acknowledge, that <hi>therefore that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs came upon them:</hi> And when <hi>Malefactors</hi> at the place of <hi>Execution;</hi> and <hi>debauched livers</hi> in ſome notable Calamities, and eſpecially in the near proſpect of <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Eternity</hi> under ſome ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſtroke of Gods Hand, accuſe themſelves, and attribute thoſe ſeverities to their particular Crimes: What Reaſon hath any man to give their ſufferings a <hi>milder name</hi> than they give them themſelves?</p>
                  <p>And thus have I given you the beſt <hi>Characters</hi> I could, by which to diſcern <hi>Divine Judgments</hi> from <hi>Providences</hi> of a like ſeverity, befalling men on other accounts: my <hi>fifth Head.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">VI. The <hi>ſixth</hi> follows: to wit, <hi>[To give you di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in the making application of Divine Judgments
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45297:21"/>to particular Caſes, without offending againſt Juſtice or Charity.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Reaſon why ſuch directions are needful, is very evident. For we are forbidden by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.1.</note> 
                     <hi>to judge</hi> our Brethren, <hi>leſt we alſo be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> And in the noted Caſes of thoſe on whom the <hi>Tower in</hi> Siloe <hi>fell,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 13.1, 2, 3.</note> and thoſe <hi>whoſe blood</hi> Pilate <hi>mingled with their Sacrifices;</hi> our Lord ſeems to take the part of the <hi>Sufferers</hi> againſt their <hi>Cenſures.</hi> And the miſcarriage of <hi>Jobs friends</hi> in their deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with him,<note place="margin">Iob 42.7.</note> is by God himſelf expreſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. Wherefore, it is meet this Caſe ſhould be carefully ſtated, that we may (in the preſent Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument) be ſatisfied, how far we may lawfully go in applying Gods Judgments, ſo as to preſerve our ſelves from ſuch Errours. And in <hi>Anſwer</hi> to this Caſe, I ſhall (as I did on the <hi>former</hi> Head) <hi>firſt</hi> premiſe ſome <hi>Grounds</hi> to proceed on; and thence proceed to the <hi>direct ſolution</hi> of it according to them.</p>
                  <p n="1">[1. The <hi>Grounds</hi> which I ſhall premiſe, are theſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1.] That it follows from what was ſaid on the <hi>former Head,</hi> that in ſuch Applications of Divine Judgments to particular Caſes, we are to be very cautelous and circumſpect.</p>
                  <p n="2">2.] And yet it does not follow, that we are totally obliged to forbear them. Yea, rather, there are divers Arguments from Scripture, which give great countenance, and (in ſome Caſes) great encouragement, to the making of them.</p>
                  <p n="1">(1. As <hi>firſt,</hi> the <hi>Text</hi> it ſelf, which aſſerts ſuch <hi>Judgments</hi> to be means whereby <hi>God is made known,</hi> will neceſſarily infer, that in order to the making this uſe of them, we muſt be allowed the liberty of diſcreet and conſiderate <hi>Application</hi> of them.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45297:21"/>For to ſuppoſe a notable <hi>Judgment executed</hi> with ſignal manifeſtation of a Divine Hand therein, and of purpoſe deſigned for men to take notice of it: and yet, not to allow them to obſerve it in thoſe circumſtances which render it moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, (all which circumſtances are neceſſarily annexed to particular Caſes) implies a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
                  <p n="2">(2. The Scripture tells us of Holy Men who have made ſuch <hi>particular Applications,</hi> and have not been <hi>blamed,</hi> but rather <hi>commended</hi> for it: and their examples left on ſacred Record for the imitation of future Times. It is given as an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable character in general of good and holy men, that becauſe they have <hi>pleaſure</hi> in that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,<note place="margin">Pſal. 111.2.</note> they <hi>ſeek out the great works of the Lord,</hi> of which theſe judicial Providences are a ſpecial part. And holy <hi>David</hi> propounds himſelf in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, as an encouraging example to patient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the Iſſue in that ſtumbling Caſe of Divine Providence, <hi>[The notable proſperity of ſome notorious wicked men]</hi> telling us, that <hi>he</hi> himſelf <hi>had ſeen</hi> ſome <hi>ſuch in great power,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.35, 36.</note> (probably <hi>Saul</hi> and his profane Courtiers and Favourites) <hi>flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing like a green Bay-tree;</hi> whom yet he obſerved in the Iſſue notably extirpated, ſo that <hi>they could not be found.</hi> And that notable ſpeech of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> to the <hi>Levites,</hi> is recorded to his commendation, (as a conſiderable part of that which gave him juſt Title to that honourable character, that he <hi>did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord, according to all that his father</hi> David <hi>bad done</hi>) wherein he obſerves particularly, (though with reflection up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>father Ahaz</hi>) that the Lord had lately <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered</hi> Judah <hi>to trouble and aſtoniſhment,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Chron. 29.2, 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> 
                     <hi>and hiſſing and that their fathers fell by the Sword, and their ſons, and daughters, and wives,</hi> were yet in capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45297:22"/>for <hi>the neglect of Gods Houſe;</hi> which he thence quickens the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> for the future to take more care of.</p>
                  <p n="3">(3. <hi>Good</hi> men in general are <hi>encouraged</hi> with the <hi>promiſed proſpect</hi> of <hi>Divine Judgments</hi> on ſome notorious wicked men. <hi>When the wicked</hi> (ſuch whoſe proſperity was a tentation to good men to <hi>fret</hi> and be <hi>envious</hi> againſt them) <hi>are cut off, thou</hi> (ſays the Pſalmiſt to the man whom he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth <hi>to wait on the Lord and keep his way</hi>) <hi>ſhalt ſee it,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.34.</note> 
                     <hi>i. e.</hi> ſo as to take notice of it to thy great ſatisfaction and encouragement to depend on God for the future. And elſewhere, the <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous</hi> is told, that when the notorious oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Judges, againſt whom that Pſalm is dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, ſhall <hi>be taken away as with a whirlwind li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and in Gods wrath, i. e.</hi> brought in the prime of their proſperity to a ſudden and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent end;<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.10.</note> that he ſhall <hi>rejoyce when he ſeeth the vengeance:</hi> and <hi>waſh his feet in the blood of the wicked, i. e.</hi> in a kind of holy Triumph for the manifeſtation of Divine Juſtice, ſhall even tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon them when they lye in their blood, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear of defilement, (to which in other caſes the Jews by the Law for touching any thing of a dead Corps were liable) any more than if they had <hi>waſhed</hi> their <hi>feet</hi> in <hi>water.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">(4. And <hi>ſinners</hi> are <hi>blamed,</hi> for not drawing Arguments of <hi>caution</hi> and <hi>reformation</hi> from the particular Inſtances of Gods Judgments in their days. As <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> for that when he ſaw and knew how God had dealt with his proud <hi>Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father Nebuchadnezzar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 5.18, 19, 20, 21, 22.</note> he notwithſtanding <hi>lifted himſelf up againſt</hi> the ſame <hi>God,</hi> before whom he ought on that conſideration to <hi>have been hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</hi> And the remaining <hi>Tribes of</hi> Judah and <hi>Benjamin</hi> are ſeverely taxed, for that <hi>when they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45297:22"/>ſaw</hi> that God had rejected and ſent into Captivity the <hi>Ten Tribes,</hi> their brethren, for their Idolatry; yet <hi>they</hi> feared not, but went on confidently in the ſame provoking ſin themſelves And it is not to be underſtood how any perſons can be obliged to take <hi>warning</hi> from particular Examples, if they be not allowed to apply ſuch Providences of God to them, in thoſe particulars from whence that <hi>caution</hi> is to be gathered.</p>
                  <p n="3">3.] Wherefore we muſt find out ſome <hi>other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation</hi> of thoſe <hi>Scriptures,</hi> which ſeem total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to prohibit all applications of Divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to particular Caſes: and particularly of <hi>thoſe before mentioned.</hi> And that (as to them at leaſt) is a matter of no great difficulty. For the <hi>firſt</hi> of them forbids <hi>one</hi> Chriſtian indeed to <hi>judge another:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat 7.1.</note> but it is only a raſh and a harſh cenſuring Chriſtian brethren (as the Phariſees were wont to do) even for the ſmalleſt faults; and that when the cenſurers themſelves, it may be, (as they) indulge themſelves in greater, (ſuch as are like <hi>beams</hi> to the others <hi>motes,</hi> as appears, <hi>v.</hi> 2.) that is there forbidden.<note place="margin">Luke 13.1, 2.</note> And the blame which in the <hi>ſecond Text,</hi> the relaters of the <hi>fall of the Tower of</hi> Siloe, and the mixing the <hi>blood of the</hi> Galileans <hi>with their Sacrifices by</hi> Pilate, did incur; was not barely for taking notice of theſe Events as Divine Judgments, but for judging the perſons (in a like <hi>Phariſaical</hi> pride) <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſinners than others,</hi> and than themſelves in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; having no other evidence to ground that cenſure, than that what they ſuffered was more ſevere than what uſually befell others; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was none at all. And <hi>Jobs</hi> friends (the <hi>third</hi> Text) were cenſured by God for making the like uncharitable and unwarrantable Inference from his Providential ſeverities upon <hi>Job.</hi> So
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45297:23"/>that all theſe Scriptures thus interpreted, (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they muſt be) make nothing againſt the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of a modeſt, ſober, prudent, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet application of Divine Judgments to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular caſes; ſeeing in an application ſo qualified, we ſhall be ſecure from offending againſt <hi>Juſtice</hi> or <hi>Charity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">[2. And therefore I proceed, in the next place, to give you the Directions promiſed you to preſerve you from ſo offending, in like applications of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſeverities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">(1. <hi>Firſt</hi> then, <hi>Privately</hi> and in our <hi>own boſoms,</hi> we may with more <hi>freedom</hi> and <hi>latitude</hi> make ſuch applications, than we may <hi>diſcourſe</hi> them withal to <hi>others:</hi> if withal we take care to turn our inward ſentiments only to thoſe uſes, which reflect Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to God, and benefit to our ſelves; without gratifying any unlawful Paſſion, apt on ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions to be ſtirred towards our ſuffering brethren, and neighbours. And yet,</p>
                  <p n="2">(2. When <hi>Gods Providence</hi> it ſelf makes any Caſe <hi>notorious</hi> by producing an offender, as it were, and chaſtiſing him upon a <hi>publick Theater,</hi> the caſe being clear and evident of it ſelf in the eyes of all men; no man is then bound up from bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his part in the <hi>publick diſcourſe:</hi> but (as he hath a call either by office, or occaſional chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the ſouls of men to take notice of it) every one may, nay ought, to ſerve Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign therein, by making uſe of it for others, as well as his own, <hi>edification.</hi> And it is related as a thing imitable in the primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that they interpreted the ſudden deaths of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> as remarkable Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and not only were poſſeſſed with great fear themſelves on that occaſion,<note place="margin">Acts 5.11.</note> but alſo derived that fear to many others, by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45297:23"/>it, ſo that <hi>they feared</hi> likewiſe as many as <hi>heard</hi> of it.</p>
                  <p n="3">(3. We are not ſo much in danger of <hi>offending againſt Juſtice</hi> or <hi>Charity</hi> in the application of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Judgments, when they befall <hi>great Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities</hi> and Societies of men, as when they light only on <hi>particular Perſons,</hi> or <hi>ſmaller Parties.</hi> For when Nations and other great Communities fall under great <hi>Epidemical calamities,</hi> wherein <hi>every member</hi> ſome way or other ſuffers, or at leaſt is endangered to ſuffer; there God himſelf expects his hand ſhould be publiquely acknowledged, and due means uſed by religious Addreſſes to him ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly and generally made for the removing of them; and in them requires that <hi>each Member</hi> bear a part, and accuſe himſelf and be deeply humbled, as being a partaker in that guilt which procured them: So that what <hi>every one</hi> is obliged to own, is without injury or breach of charity im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable to them <hi>all.</hi> Whereas there are very few <hi>private Caſes,</hi> wherein the Perſons ſuffering can be convincingly brought by others under a like obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to own and acknowledge the particulars char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on them by their Cenſurers, as the Cauſes for which they ſo ſuffer: and ſo we are endangered to charge them at adventure, and therein to be unjuſt and uncharitable.</p>
                  <p n="4">(4. We run leſs hazard of violating <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> in applying ſuch <hi>Divine ſtrokes,</hi> as <hi>Judgments</hi> to <hi>ſome</hi> perſons, than to <hi>others.</hi> For whereas there are ſome <hi>notoriouſly bad men,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 3.9.</note> who <hi>publiſh their ſin as</hi> Sodom, and proclaim them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>to have no fear of God before their eyes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 3.18. Pſal. 14.3.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>altogether become filthy</hi> or <hi>ſtinking</hi> (as the <hi>Margin</hi> hath it) in the noſtrils of all ſerious and ſober perſons; ſo that no <hi>Charity,</hi> be it never ſo large, (except it be wilfully blind withal) can
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45297:24"/>judge better of them: when any remarkable hand of God finds theſe perſons out, to ſeize them for publique Exemplary puniſhment, I cannot ſee, why we may not, without any heſitation in a caſe ſo plain, think and ſay, <hi>This is a remarkable Judgment of God; and a fair warning to all men to avoid ſuch courſes.</hi> And eſpecially if ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have arrived to that height of profeſſed wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs as to <hi>glory in their ſhame</hi> at that rate,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.19. Pſal. 1.1.</note> as to ſet themſelves down in the <hi>ſeat of the ſcornful,</hi> and ſcoff Religion and Vertue out of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as a thing deſpicable and contemptible; and to own themſelves in all companies, as the publique <hi>Hectors</hi> and Champions of prophaneneſs and impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and profeſſed <hi>perſecuters</hi> of all perſons that dare appear on the ſide of God and goodneſs. For in ſuch caſes, as I told you before, the opinion of all the world juſtifies us, in making the ſevereſt refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions upon their ſufferings.</p>
                  <p>But when ſufferers, though the hand of God lie heavy upon them, are either eminently <hi>good</hi> men, or ſuch as in the judgment of rational cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we are bound to <hi>think well of</hi> for the main, though they have their allay of humane frailty, and are <hi>Gold,</hi> though mixed with <hi>droſs;</hi> yea, or ſuch, as there is hope they may become <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> becauſe there is nothing that declares them <hi>deſperately</hi> and <hi>incorrigibly bad:</hi> We are towards all theſe ſorts of men to proceed in cenſuring with far greater Caution, and the better they are, the more muſt be obſerved; according to the <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing meaſures.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1.) That we endeavour to be as <hi>ſparing</hi> in <hi>applying</hi> theſe ſorts of Divine Providences, to the caſes of particular perſons under the former cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters as God is in <hi>inflicting</hi> them; and appear as loth and unwilling to do the <hi>one,</hi> as he to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:45297:24"/>do the <hi>other.</hi> For it is very uncharitable for any man to be over-forward in crying out, upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unuſual ſtroke upon another, <hi>A Judgment, a Judgment;</hi> becauſe thereby he cruelly vexeth his brothers ſores; a thing which is done by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than by exaggerating his calamities with the repreſentation of Gods diſpleaſure te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in them. Beſides, that the <hi>haſtineſs</hi> of men in ſuch applications, looks too much like that diſpoſition which <hi>Charity</hi> diſclaims,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.6.</note> of <hi>rejoycing in iniquity, i. e.</hi> in the opportunity of coloura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble laying a criminal matter to ones brothers charge, without ſtaying to examine what ground there is for it: as on the contrary, to <hi>rejoyce in the Truth, i. e.</hi> to be glad when by the diſcovery of the truth, our own and others ſuſpicions or miſappre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions concerning him are removed, and he vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated, is a <hi>charitable Temper,</hi> as the Apoſtle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2.) That we do not firſt <hi>fancy</hi> a <hi>Divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in our own thoughts to have befaln ſuch a <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Party</hi> as we do not affect; and then <hi>ſearch out iniquities,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 64.6.</note> (in the Pſalmiſts Phraſe) or make a ſtrict Inquiſition, to find out criminal mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in him to apply it unto, for the juſtification of our own cenſure. For this is a prepoſterous inverting of the Rules of Juſtice, which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wont to pronounce ſentence firſt at all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, and then examine the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>whether there be any cauſe:</hi> and a great breach of <hi>Charity</hi> alſo, as implying a malicious deſign againſt our brother, which we ſeek an opportunity to execute.</p>
                  <p>This ſeems to be the fault of thoſe <hi>Diſciples</hi> themſelves, who enquired of Chriſt concerning the <hi>man that was born blind:</hi> for they firſt reſolve upon it, that this was a <hi>Judgment of God</hi> on him for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:45297:25"/>
                     <hi>ſome ſin;</hi> and then they came to our Saviour to reſolve them,<note place="margin">Joh. 9.2.</note> 
                     <hi>for whoſe ſin it was, his own, or his Parents?</hi> And it ſeems evident, by the whole car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of their diſcourſes, that <hi>Jobs friends,</hi> though they unanimouſly firſt conclude among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that his ſufferings were <hi>Divine Judgments</hi> upon him for ſome <hi>foul crime;</hi> yet they are at a loſs what crime of that nature to find him guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of, and therefore they tax him at all adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, with all the horrid Crimes they can imagine, to draw a confeſſion from him at leaſt of ſome of them, for the juſtification of their own uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cenſure.</p>
                  <p n="3">3.) That we do not <hi>haſtily</hi> call ſuch ſevere Providences of God towards ſuch particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>Judgments,</hi> whom we can charge with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is notoriouſly ſinful, in the <hi>general Judgment</hi> of <hi>all Mankind,</hi> or at leaſt, of <hi>all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi> For it is a great piece of <hi>uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> as well as <hi>injuſtice,</hi> which is too ordinarily practiſed in ſuch places where the common Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity is crumbled into <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Parties;</hi> for diſſenters of all ſides to impute the ſufferings befalling their <hi>oppoſites,</hi> to Divine diſpleaſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them for holding ſuch opinions as differ foom theirs, or practiſing in ſome particulars o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than they do. Now this ariſeth ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily from a <hi>partial fondneſs</hi> which every one hath for his <hi>own opinion</hi> or <hi>way:</hi> which inclines him to think <hi>God</hi> hath as great a <hi>kindneſs</hi> for it as himſelf, and his Party have: and to conclude all his Providences to be accordingly engaged to ſerve under thoſe banners of diſtinction, under which he hath liſted himſelf: whence ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons find it eaſie (upon every unuſual ſtroke of God upon any that are not every way agreeable to their humour) to conclude, that the very
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:45297:25"/>point in difference betwixt them is judged by God and their oppoſites, confuted from Heaven by a <hi>Demonſtration</hi> of Divine diſpleaſure againſt them. And ſuch an unhappy Paralogiſm as this, we are told by our Hiſtorians, it was, which in the dark times of Popery gave the cauſe, in the opinion of an whole <hi>Synod,</hi> againſt the <hi>married Clergy,</hi> when the <hi>ſide of the Room where the maintainers of it ſat fell down, killing ſome, and burting others.</hi> For thereupon they that were for <hi>Prieſts ſingle life,</hi> cryed down the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of the <hi>faln Party</hi> with them, as witneſſed againſt by God himſelf; and by that ſorry Argument and Noiſe prevailed. Now againſt this great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake (by the way) we ſhall never be ſufficiently armed except we govern our Apprehenſions by theſe <hi>Two Principles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>(1.) That God never appointed the <hi>dark Rule of Providence</hi> (to us it is no other) to judge <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> by, whether right or wrong, good or bad.<note place="margin">Judg. 20. 21, 25.</note> Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes, for <hi>ſecret ends</hi> of his own, he blaſts a good, and proſpers a bad cauſe, as the <hi>had Cauſe</hi> of the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> in two ſet Battels, againſt the <hi>good Cauſe</hi> of the Eleven <hi>Tribes:</hi> and the horrid and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Impoſture of the <hi>Mahometans</hi> hath now for many Ages, by the permiſſion of Providence, proſpered wonderfully againſt the greateſt part of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world.</item>
                     <item>(2.) That <hi>Gods great and ſignal Judgments,</hi> of which we are diſcourſing, are now adays <hi>rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inflicted,</hi> but for ſuch Crimes as are generally condemned in the <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>all Mankind,</hi> or at leaſt, <hi>the generality of Chriſtians,</hi> according as he deſigns the notice of them to be ſpread in a greater or narrower compaſs. And the Reaſon is evident, to wit, becauſe it cannot otherwiſe be rationally expected, the Juſtice of them ſhould
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45297:26"/>be clearly and convincingly owned, and ſo the good they are intended for muſt needs be hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſo many as are diſſatisfied in the merit of the Cauſe that is taken to procure them. But when a Divine ſeverity juſtly makes an example of any perſon in the general opinion notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly criminous; they are <hi>all inexcuſable, who thenceforward do the ſame things they condemned in another,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 2.1.</note> (as the Apoſtle ſaith) and confeſs Gods Judgment to have righteouſly befaln him for.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="4">4.) That we <hi>publiſh</hi> not <hi>on the houſe tops</hi> (in our Saviours phraſe on another occaſion) that which is,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.27.</note> it may be, <hi>whiſpered in our ears</hi> only; and few, poſſibly no other perſons know of. For it may ſo fall out, that our intimate <hi>acquaintance</hi> with ſome men, and their circumſtances, may give us knowledge of their <hi>particular vices,</hi> ſecret as to all the reſt of the world; and of Gods <hi>ſecret ſtrokes</hi> befalling them in their perſons or private concerns, which we in our own thoughts may rationally conclude to be Divine Judgments in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted for them. Now in ſuch Caſes, though we may with great charity declare our apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions hereof to the <hi>parties concerned</hi> themſelves, and admoniſh, and exhort them on that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; yet it were great uncharitableneſs to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to others either the <hi>one</hi> or the <hi>other.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For, when God intends (as appears by his way of proceeding therein) only a <hi>private correction;</hi> it muſt proceed from a <hi>defect</hi> of <hi>charity</hi> in us, if we by divulging it, turn it into a <hi>publique Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,</hi> to the expoſing our Brother to an open ſhame. And the very juſtice of every <hi>petty School</hi> may convince us of the evil of ſo doing; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the corrections given within thoſe walls are forbidden to be divulged, under a like penalty
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:45297:26"/>to that which the diſgraced School-fellow ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered.</p>
                  <p n="5">5.) That we <hi>apply</hi> not the ſevere ſtrokes of God upon our neighbour to the ſatisfaction of our <hi>private ſpleen</hi> and <hi>revengeful Humour:</hi> which is too ordinary when we think ſuch as lie under them have wronged us, (or it may be they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally have ſo) and we conclude, their ſufferings are <hi>Divine Judgments</hi> befalling them on our Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel. This was the uncharitable Conſure of <hi>Shimei</hi> againſt <hi>David,</hi> when he tells him that <hi>God had avenged on him the blood of the Houſe of</hi> Saul, by the <hi>Rebellion</hi> of <hi>Abſalom.</hi> For it is plain by the Text,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 16.5, 6, 7, 8.</note> that <hi>Shimei</hi> was of the very <hi>family of</hi> Saul: and it may be looked upon himſelf, as in ſome probable vicinity to the <hi>Crown,</hi> if the ſucceſſion of it had continued in <hi>that family.</hi> At leaſt 'tis probable, that by the tranſlating it from thence, he found his hopes (as to thoſe preferments and other advantages which uſually are attained at Court by thoſe of the Royal Blood) blaſted and defeated. It is true indeed that Gods Juſtice doth ſometimes appear in the remarkable vindication of eminently good mens, and his uſeful Inſtruments. Cauſes: but for every ordinary perſon upon every petty trifling injury, to expect that he ſhould do the like for him, or ſuppoſe he doth it, is too great a Preſumption.</p>
                  <p n="6">6.) That we judge not our Brethrens <hi>eſtate towards God,</hi> and much leſs their <hi>future eſtate</hi> from the moſt evident Judgments temporally befalling them.</p>
                  <p n="1">(1.) Not their <hi>preſent eſtate towards God.</hi> For a ſore Judgment may befall a man greatly in Gods favour, for a foul Crime; as in the caſe of the <hi>Death of</hi> Davids <hi>child,</hi> inflicted, even after his Repentance, for thoſe hainous ſins of <hi>Adultery</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:45297:27"/>and <hi>Murder;</hi> becauſe he had by them <hi>cauſed the Enemies of God to blaſpheme;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.14.</note> doth evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) And much leſs muſt we thence judge their <hi>future eſtate</hi> in another world. For there is no ſufficient cauſe to judge even <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lev. 10.3. 1 Sam. 6.19. 2 Sam. 6.7.</note> the inquiſitive <hi>Bethſhemites, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah,</hi> and others, damned; though God ſmote them dead in unwarrantable actions. Yea, even <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> themſelves died by a Divine Sentence in the Wilderneſs for their <hi>ſin at</hi> Meribah: and yet one of them <hi>(Moſes)</hi> we have ſufficient evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is in glory:<note place="margin">Mat. 17.3.</note> and have no reaſon to doubt the caſe of the <hi>other.</hi> Yea, men may be <hi>judged of the Lord,</hi> (in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſuppoſition) when chaſtened with <hi>ſickneſs</hi> and <hi>death</hi> extraordinary, <hi>that they may not be condemned with the world:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.30, 31, 32. 1 Cor. 5.5.</note> and an offender <hi>delivered even to Satan,</hi> may ſuffer <hi>to the deſtruction of the fleſh, that his ſpirit may be ſaved in the day of the Lord, i. e.</hi> in the private Judgment which he undergoes from the Lord at his death.</p>
                  <p n="7">7.) That we aſſign not <hi>particular ſins</hi> as the ſpecial Cauſes of a Divine Judgment too <hi>perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorily;</hi> except where the circumſtances notoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evince it by the <hi>Rules before given,</hi> or ſome of them at leaſt. For if we be therein miſtaken in our Judgment; yea, if there be no moral cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty that we are not miſtaken, (ſuch as may rationally convince the perſons concerned and others thereof) the <hi>end</hi> which we are ſuppoſed to deſign by ſuch application, (to wit, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>particular ſin</hi> to which we attribute the procuring that Judgment more <hi>formidable</hi>) is loſt upon thoſe whom we particularly intend to benefit by it, and others too: and we our ſelves are liable to be cenſured, for putting an
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:45297:27"/>uncharitable brand upon our brother without a cauſe.</p>
                  <p n="8">8.) That we <hi>vaunt</hi> not, or <hi>magnifie our ſelves</hi> againſt our ſuffering Brother, by <hi>comparing</hi> our ſelves with him, as if we were therefore the <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter men,</hi> becauſe we <hi>fare better</hi> at Gods Hands he. This is one property of <hi>Charity,</hi> (among the many excellent characters given it by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) that it <hi>vaunts not it ſelf,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.4.</note> (<hi>i. e.</hi> with the diminution of a mans brethren, for elſe it were rather a deſcription of Humility than Charity) nor is, upon ſuch an account, <hi>puffed up.</hi> And the moſt uncharitable account upon which any man can <hi>vaunt</hi> to the leſſening of his brother; is, when it is done meerly upon the difference that Gods only pleaſure makes betwixt the one and the other. This (among many others) was one great piece of uncharitableneſs in <hi>Jobs friends,</hi> that having in his ſad ſufferings taxed him with being of the number of thoſe whom God had ſignally branded with remarkable Judgments, and a partner in guilt with thoſe of the <hi>old world whoſe foundation was overflown with a flood,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job 22.15, 16, 20, 21, 29, 30.</note> though he were differenced in his puniſhment, being a ſufferer by the contrary Element of <hi>fire;</hi> they in the mean while boaſt, that <hi>their ſubſtance was not cut down,</hi> as being men more <hi>acquainted with</hi> God, more <hi>humble,</hi> more <hi>innocent;</hi> as they imply, when they adviſe <hi>Job</hi> upon their experience to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo too.</p>
                  <p n="9">9.) That we make no mans <hi>religious living</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, or eminent <hi>profeſſion</hi> of it, (no not though we have ſome cauſe to think him declined from it now) by objecting it to him under ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a <hi>part</hi> of his <hi>calamity:</hi> nor occaſion him whilſt he ſuffers <hi>under Gods hand</hi> to ſuffer for <hi>his ſake</hi> too: A thing too uſual, when <hi>bad</hi> men apply the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:45297:28"/>Judgments of God (or thoſe which they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret to be ſuch) to <hi>good</hi> men, or thoſe who have had a reputation to be ſuch, beyond their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. For this is to give them (as the Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors did to our Saviour) <hi>gall and vinegar to drink,</hi> when they have already <hi>bitterneſs</hi> enough upon their ſpirits from the <hi>Cup</hi> of their <hi>Croſs,</hi> that God appoints them to <hi>drink off.</hi> This was to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> as he tells us, <hi>like a Sword in his</hi> bones, when profane men ſaid to him in his affliction, <hi>Where is now thy God?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.10.</note> and when they caſt in his Teeth, (as their ſucceſſors did afterwards in our Saviours) his former <hi>truſting in God,</hi> as if it had either been Hypocritical,<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2.1, 8, 9.</note> or (if real) miſplaced on one that had thus forſaken him. Now to deal thus with our neighbour, is at all times greatly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable. For it either argues an hard <hi>cenſure</hi> of him that he is an <hi>hypocrite;</hi> or a greater and fouler <hi>affront,</hi> if we do not ſo eſteem him; for then we <hi>turn</hi> (as the ſame Pſalmiſt elſewhere taxeth men of the ſame uncharitable temper) <hi>his glory into ſhame,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.2.</note> and endeavour to make that a matter of diſgrace to him which is really moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable.</p>
                  <p n="10">10.) In a word: That we do not <hi>rejoyce, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult,</hi> or <hi>triumph</hi> over any man under Gods hand, upon any account; much leſs <hi>revile,</hi> and <hi>reproach</hi> him; but really <hi>pitty, bewail,</hi> and <hi>condole</hi> with him rather; and (as we have opportunity) <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, admoniſh, comfort,</hi> and <hi>pray</hi> for him. For to do the <hi>former,</hi> is the conſtant guiſe of thoſe that (in the character of Gods Holy Spirit in the Scripture) are marked for <hi>wicked</hi> men. The Heathen <hi>Edomites</hi> were ſuch;<note place="margin">Obad. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and they <hi>rejoyced in the day of</hi> Judah's <hi>diſtreſs.</hi> Davids <hi>Enemies,</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo to him on Gods account) were ſuch; <hi>and in his adverſity they rejoyced.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 35.13.</note> Our <hi>Saviours Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:45297:28"/>were ſuch; and as <hi>they judged him ſmitten of God,</hi> they <hi>ſhaked their heads</hi> at him upon the Croſs,<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.4. See Mat. 27.40, 41, 42, 43, 44. Mark 15.29, &amp;c.</note> and reviled him with moſt unſavoury and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſpeeches.</p>
                  <p>And although there be ſeveral Paſſages in Scripture which ſeem to propound Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as a <hi>glad ſpectacle</hi> to good men, and a matter of <hi>rejoycing,</hi> when they befall thoſe that are notoriouſly <hi>wicked:</hi> As when it is propheſied, <hi>That the righteous ſhall rejoyce when he ſeeth the vengeance,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.10.</note> And when God calls on all the Saints even in glory,<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.2.</note> (the <hi>holy Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> eſpecially) to <hi>rejoyce</hi> and triumph over <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Babylon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet it is to be obſerved, that theſe and the like Texts relate only to ſuch as were <hi>Gods pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and notorious enemies:</hi> and the joy and triumph required or allowed, in their deſtruction, is only upon account of the <hi>ſucceſs of his cauſe</hi> againſt them, and the vindication of his Glory and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts. As appears remarkably in the <hi>Pſalm</hi> quoted, wherein he tells us, how the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſhould expreſs their joy, to wit, by taking notice, that <hi>verily there is a reward for the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 58.11.</note> and that <hi>verily he is a God that judgeth in the earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the <hi>latter</hi> diſpoſitions and deportments are recommended to us by the Examples of the <hi>beſt men,</hi> and moſt <hi>eminent</hi> of <hi>Saints.</hi> When <hi>Jobs friends</hi> had dealt ſo uncharitably with him, he tells them what a different uſage they ſhould have found from him, <hi>if their ſouls had been in his ſouls ſtead;</hi> and aſſures them, that though he could in ſuch a caſe have <hi>ſpoken as they did to him</hi> now, and <hi>heaped up words againſt them,</hi> and <hi>ſhaken his head</hi> at their calamity, as they uſed him: yet he would have <hi>ſtrengthned them with his mouth, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:45297:29"/>the moving of his lips ſhould have aſſwaged their grief.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job 16.4, 5.</note> And when <hi>Davids</hi> very <hi>bitter enemies,</hi> that inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted over his calamity, <hi>were ſick,</hi> he <hi>cloathed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with ſackcloth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 35.13.</note> 
                     <hi>and his prayers,</hi> though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefully received by them, and thrown back in ſcorn <hi>into his boſom,</hi> whence they proceeded, were heartily and ſincerely from that <hi>boſom</hi> poured out to God for them. And our <hi>Saviour,</hi> the moſt perfect of men, to the many ſufferers under Gods hand whom he relieved, was generally ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate; that he <hi>took on him,</hi> by a merciful Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy, <hi>all the Infirmities</hi> that he cured, and <hi>bare all</hi> his Patients <hi>ſickneſſes.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 8.17.</note> Yea, he could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear <hi>weeping</hi> over the very proſpect of thoſe Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies he foretold himſelf againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> though the <hi>Shambles of his Prophets,</hi> and his own <hi>Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-houſe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 19.41.</note> And God expects, (as well as the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers themſelves) <hi>that to him that is afflicted pity ſhould be ſhewn;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job 6.14.19.21, 22.</note> eſpecially, <hi>if the hand of the Lord hath touched him:</hi> and diſlikes that men (in their brethrens calamities) <hi>ſhould perſecute like him, i. e.</hi> take the ſame liberty of harſh and ſevere uſage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, as God does, as if they could do it with like right and juſtice as he. In a word, it is his expreſs command, that to ſhew our ſelves to <hi>be of the ſame mind one towards another,</hi> we not only <hi>rejoyce with them that rejoyce,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 12.15, 16.</note> but <hi>weep alſo with thoſe that weep.</hi> And thus I diſcharge this <hi>ſixth</hi> Head alſo.</p>
                  <p n="7">VII. Come we now to the <hi>ſeventh</hi> and laſt, to <hi>draw ſuch Inferences</hi> from this whole diſcourſe as may be of uſe and advantage to us.</p>
                  <p n="1">[1. And <hi>firſt,</hi> I infer the great Reaſon that there is for a <hi>general Judgment</hi> in another world. For, <hi>ſeeing God is known by the Judgment that he exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth;</hi> and all that which he executeth here, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends but to a few offenders; and it may be, the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:45297:29"/>notice taken of thoſe <hi>Executions</hi> that are made, reacheth but a <hi>ſmall part</hi> of Mankind: it ſtands with the higheſt Reaſon, that there ſhould be a Time wherein all the world may ſee (even thoſe that <hi>while his hand was lifted up</hi> on earth <hi>would not ſee</hi>) that <hi>juſt and true are his Judgments.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 26.11.</note> Beſides, by the rareneſs of the <hi>Judgments he executeth</hi> here, inſtead of <hi>being known</hi> as he ought, he is by many apt to be <hi>miſunderſtood;</hi> whilſt they are generally ſtumbled at his letting ſo many notorious offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders eſcape for one that he puniſheth: and thoſe that eſcape he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, many times are the greateſt and moſt proſperous of men, that even dare his juſtice, by <hi>ſetting their mouths againſt the Heavens</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.9.</note> Wherefore, that he may make it known, that he ſpareth not ſo many <hi>high and mighty offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> either through impotency, or partiality; it is eaſie to infer, that there muſt be ſuch a day, wherein <hi>all men, whether they be ſmall or great, ſhall ſtand before him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 20.12.</note> 
                     <hi>and be judged according to their works.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">[2. I infer, that thoſe men <hi>do God great diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> who either careleſly <hi>overlook,</hi> or deſignedly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to <hi>ſuppreſs</hi> and keep from the notice of the world, theſe <hi>remarkable Divine Judgments:</hi> or (when by reaſon of their own publique circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances they cannot but be taken notice of by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) attempt to ſlur, and ſtifle as much as they can, the evidence of thoſe particularities which ſo much conduce to the preſerving and propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>knowledge of God</hi> in the world. Thoſe of the <hi>former</hi> ſort are injurious in an high degree to God; who, when he expoſeth his glorious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes to view as on a <hi>Theater,</hi> will not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to be <hi>ſpectators</hi> of them. But thoſe of the <hi>lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> rank are prodigiouſly wicked. And yet too many even of theſe are to be found in all ages of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:45297:30"/>the world, who ſtudy to darken Gods glory in ſuch remarkable Judgments, and to lead the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions that people naturally are apt to have of them, as far from God and Providence as they can find any colour to do. Thus the <hi>Egyptian Magicians</hi> (encouraged by a prophane Atheiſtical King, as well as prompted thereto, by their own malice) emulated the miracles that <hi>Moſes</hi> did, and by frequent attempts to do the like; endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to perſuade the People, that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in them beyond the power of created be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to effect; till God at laſt in the <hi>plague of the Lice,</hi> drew from them an unwilling confeſſion, that neither they nor their maſter the Devil could imitate it,<note place="margin">Exod. 8.19.</note> and that therefore it was the <hi>finger of God.</hi> And it ſeems to me, that the <hi>Prieſts and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viners</hi> of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> were willing (when they were called into conſultation what to do with the <hi>Ark of God</hi>) to have carried on as bad a deſign, and to have perſuaded both themſelves and the people that it was a diſputable caſe, <hi>whether</hi> the <hi>God of Iſrael</hi> had inflicted thoſe Judgments upon them,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 6.9.</note> which they had ſuffered; or whether it were a meer <hi>chance that had befaln them.</hi> And therefore, though they ſpeak ſome good words concerning the God of Iſrael, and give their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that if they returned the <hi>Ark,</hi> they ſhould make him ſome <hi>Preſents</hi> too, (it may be forced thereunto, as <hi>Caiaphas</hi> propheſied, by a Divine impulſe) yet they contrive to put the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that great Queſtion upon the iſſue of ſuch an <hi>odd Experiment,</hi> as without a miraculous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the Lord of all the Creatures upon thoſe that they imployed, would in all rational probability have determined it againſt God. For it was ten thouſand to one odds, but that the <hi>Kine</hi> (being <hi>milch Kine,</hi> and their <hi>Calves newly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:45297:30"/>taken</hi> from their <hi>ſides,</hi> and <hi>ſhut up</hi> in their ſight, juſt as they were put into the Cart, that was by their advice to carry the Ark) being let looſe without a driver, had turned, as nature would prompt them, the ſame way their young ones had gone, rather than towards the <hi>Land of</hi> Iſrael. And a foul ſcandal it is to the <hi>Chriſtian Name,</hi> that too many of thoſe who bear it, do herein act, as if they joyned in deſign with the fore-mentioned <hi>Heathens.</hi> For, beſides the <hi>downright Atheiſts,</hi> (too many of whom paſs muſter now adays un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſts colours) whom I have before confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; the <hi>ſottiſh</hi> and <hi>prophane generation</hi> of men are deſirous to look beſide God in all ſuch ſtrokes; leſt by confeſſing his hand in them, they ſhould be obliged to be more Religions, than ſutes the Intereſt of their Luſts. Whence, in the calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which at any time befall themſelves or others, thoſe of them who pretend to but the leaſt ſmat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering in <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> ſeek for cauſes to aſſign them to, either in the <hi>general order</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> moved when once ſet a going, without any ſpecial hand of God governing the motion of it ſelf; or in the <hi>Influence</hi> of <hi>ſuperiour Bodies</hi> upon the <hi>inferiour,</hi> by the Conjunctions and Oppoſitions, or other Aſpects of <hi>Planets,</hi> in imaginary Houſes, which the inventions of jugling Aſtrologers have built for them in the Heavens to conſult and quarrel in, about the government of the lower world; or to the <hi>diſtempers</hi> at ſome <hi>ſeaſons</hi> naturally cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting the <hi>Elements,</hi> and by them the bodies, yea and the very minds of men. Others of a lower rank in their Intellectuals, through an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant malice ſuſpect the <hi>evil Tongues</hi> of ſome perſons who have ſome way or other (and often undeſervedly) gotten an <hi>evil Name</hi> among their Neighbours; or it may be, accuſe the Devil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:45297:31"/>for <hi>paying them ſome ill turns he owed them,</hi> though they were never known to have carried themſelves ſo towards him as to deſerve any ſuch uſage from him. In all which, and the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, it is the main buſineſs of the champions of Ignorance and Prophaneneſs, to <hi>caſt a miſt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their own eyes and other mens, to obſcure the <hi>Providence</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in thoſe <hi>Judgments which he executeth,</hi> leſt he ſhould be <hi>known</hi> by them. Which certainly is a crime of the greateſt magnitude: for it argues an <hi>envy</hi> at the <hi>glory</hi> which Gods wonderful Providences are wont to procure him in the world: than which there can hardly any attempt be conceived more <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanical.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">[3. We may hence infer, How great Reaſon there is, that ſuch <hi>Judicial Providences</hi> ſhould be exactly taken <hi>notice</hi> of, and with all the notable circumſtances which moſt manifeſt God, <hi>recorded,</hi> and tranſmitted to Poſterity. The learned and judicious <hi>Lord Verulam</hi> takes notice of it as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the hiſtorical part of Learning,<note place="margin">De aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. ent. l. 2.</note> that there is not extant an impartial and well-atteſted <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoria Nemeſeos,</hi> (as he calls it) an account of the moſt remarkable Judgments of God on notorious offenders; and complains of it. And it were to be wiſhed, that God would put it into the heart of ſome <hi>ſupreme Magiſtrates</hi> to promote ſo god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Deſign by their Authority, that the <hi>great Judgments</hi> of the <hi>King of Kings</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords</hi> might be preſerved in publique avowed <hi>Records,</hi> as their <hi>own Judgments</hi> are. For certainly it would be a great check to the <hi>Atheiſm</hi> that ſo reigns in the world at this day, to have ſuch publique te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies preſerved againſt them to ſtop their prophane mouths withal, when they take liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to cry down God and Providence. And ſuch
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:45297:31"/>a work cannot be done effectually to ſuch a purpoſe, but with their encouragement and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, who are able to oblige the Relators of ſuch ſignal Providential ſtrokes, by the ſacred tye of an Oath, to <hi>ſpeak the Truth, all the Truth, and nothing but the Truth,</hi> in Gods cauſe, as well as mens: and ſeverely to puniſh thoſe perſons, who ſhall appear upon due examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>to lye for God, or againſt him.</hi> But ſeeing ſuch a deſign is rather to be wiſhed, than ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to be carried on, in ſuch an Age as this; I forbear to inſiſt longer on this Point; and in the <hi>fourth</hi> place infer,</p>
                  <p n="4">[4. That thoſe <hi>private Perſons,</hi> in the defect of more publique endeavours in this kind, do God <hi>good ſervice,</hi> and much oblige Poſterity; who take what honeſt pains they can, in ſo profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a diſcovery, by enquiring into, and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming themſelves and others from good Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, of ſuch Inſtances of Gods juſt Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as their Ages and the places they live in afford. For however ſome Atheiſtical ſpirits are, according to their wont, apt to ſlight and deſpiſe them: yet, abundance of ſerious and conſidering Perſons, do, and 'tis to be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, will, in after-Ages, make great advantages by them.</p>
                  <p n="5">[5. And yet this muſt be attempted with great <hi>care</hi> and <hi>caution,</hi> as a thing which we cannot lay out too much circumſpect diligence and induſtry. Which alſo follows from my <hi>Text</hi> and Doctrine. For thoſe <hi>Judgments</hi> by which the <hi>Lord is known,</hi> muſt be firſt <hi>known</hi> to be, and to be his <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> that is, it muſt be known that ſuch things, as to matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> are certain; and that they are accompanied with ſuch <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> as carry in them a <hi>moral certainty</hi> alſo,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:45297:32"/>(as I before told you) that they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted by God upon ſuch an account: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if there be a rational doubt of the one, or the other, there muſt be an equal uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in the concluſions drawn from ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain Premiſes.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore, it is certainly a foul and hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous crime, and a thing highly injurious both to God and man, for any Perſon or Perſons, either out of a <hi>miſguided zeal</hi> for God, or out of a particular fond <hi>affection</hi> to any <hi>Party</hi> in Religion, and much more, upon the account of any more unjuſtifiable <hi>Paſſion;</hi> to become a <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> of Divine Judgments: or a buſic reporter and ſpreader of ſuch Forgeries. For this is to <hi>ſpeak wickedly for God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.7.</note> and <hi>talk deceitfully for him;</hi> which <hi>Job</hi> chargeth with great abhorren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon his friends; as judging it a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming thing to endeavour to prop up the Cauſe of the <hi>God of Truth</hi> with <hi>falſhoods.</hi> Nor indeed is it leſs <hi>miſchievous,</hi> than it is <hi>unſutable,</hi> to the intereſt it pretends to defend. For though <hi>one</hi> or <hi>two</hi> ſuch <hi>pious frauds</hi> may prove at the firſt, (in ſome juncture of Time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſimple and well-meaning devotion prevails over the inquiſitive humour of Mankind) to be ſome way ſerviceable to the Deſign they were coined for: yet in proceſs of Time, as the ſtate of Religion alters, and men (having it, may be diſcovered the fallacy) grow more nice of belief in ſuch matters; the caſe is quite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent. For then ſtrikes in (ordinarily) the ſubtil <hi>Atheiſt</hi> or <hi>misbeliever,</hi> and aggravates the flaws he finds in ſuch ſtories, as are really ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious, to the blemiſhing the Reputation of the moſt undoubted Records of Chriſtianity it ſelf. And it can hardly be imagined what a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:45297:32"/>foul imputation upon that holy Religion of our bleſſed Saviour amongſt Atheiſts and other Infidels, thoſe Cart-loads of <hi>Monkiſh ſtories</hi> in the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> have occaſioned; wherein the <hi>Miracles</hi> of their <hi>fictitious Saints,</hi> and the <hi>Judgments</hi> of God upon their <hi>pretended Adverſaries,</hi> are equally nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; and yet both ſo groſly contrived, that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfulneſs of the bungling Inventers ſaves the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futers of them the pains of any ſtudied Arguments to diſprove them. And yet with ſuch a fottiſh credulity are the generality of that Religion poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, that there is hardly <hi>any one</hi> who was emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently <hi>inſtrumental</hi> in the <hi>Reformation,</hi> but they can tell you of ſome <hi>miraculous Judgment</hi> of God that brought him to his <hi>End;</hi> which they believe with equal faith to what they have for the Goſpel it ſelf: even that of <hi>Luthers body being carried away out of his Coffin by the Devil,</hi> which he himſelf lived to diſprove by his own Pen.</p>
                  <p>And it were well if it could be ſaid of them only, that they prop up a cauſe with <hi>lying wonders</hi> (as is propheſied of them) that <hi>needs</hi> it:<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.9.</note> and that the indiſcreet zeal of others, who would be thought to have <hi>better Conſciences,</hi> as they have (wherein they differ from them) a <hi>better Cauſe,</hi> did not make uſe of their Example too much, and treat their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of different Judgments in the petty diſputes that divide them into Parties, in the ſame unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table manner. At leaſt it were to be deſired, if ſuch hot ſpirits will needs continue (with <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Mad-man</hi>) <hi>to caſt Fire-brands</hi> one at another;<note place="margin">Prov. 26.18.</note> that they would not (with the Poets <hi>Prometheus</hi>) <hi>ſteal fire from Heaven</hi> to kindle them withall, by forging miraculous Providences to blaſt the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe Cauſes they are prejudiced againſt, in the Perſons of thoſe that defend them.</p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:45297:33"/>
                  <p n="6">[6. Laſtly, we may learn hence, on all hands, to make a <hi>more beneficial uſe</hi> of Gods Judicial Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences: to wit, that of the <hi>Text,</hi> to endeavour to advance in the <hi>knowledge of God</hi> by them. Which Duty (according to the uſual extent of that Phraſe in Scfipture) includes many particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">(1. As <hi>firſt,</hi> If any of us be ſufferers under any ſuch <hi>ſtrokes,</hi> as our own Conſciences ſuggeſt to us are <hi>Divine Judgments:</hi> we are betwixt God and our own ſouls to endeavour to take up the <hi>Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie</hi> which he ſeems to have with us betimes: and in order thereunto to acknowledge and bewail thoſe known ſins which we are convinced of; and in a more ſpecial manner, thoſe which our own hearts ſeize on in freſh purſuit as the <hi>particular</hi> cauſes of that diſpleaſure from God, under which we lie: to humble our ſelves under his mighty Hand, and remove by ſerious reformation and amendment of life, <hi>out of his ſight,</hi> whatever is offenſive to thoſe <hi>pure eyes which cannot behold evil,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hab. 1.13.</note> 
                     <hi>or look on iniquity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if it be not clear to us what <hi>particular quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel</hi> God hath with us; or that he hath an <hi>eſpecial cauſe</hi> given him beyond the ordinary frailties of humanity; ſo that (as to any known great crime) we are as clear as <hi>Job</hi> himſelf; yet we are (as he is well adviſed, and alſo of himſelf reſolves before that advice) to <hi>ſay to God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job 10.2.34.31, 32.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhew me wherefore thou contendeſt with me: and that which I ſee not, teach thou me: and if I have done iniquity, I will do ſo no more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is to be done betwixt God and our own Conſciences, if none but God and they be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with our circumſtances.</p>
                  <p>But if our <hi>Caſes</hi> and our <hi>Crimes</hi> too be already by Gods Providence expoſed to the <hi>publique notice,</hi> it is our duty in this Caſe to go farther; and to evidence our true Repentance to the world, by a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:45297:33"/>true, free, and ingenious acknowledgement, <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying God, and giving glory to him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 51.4, Joſh. 7.19.</note> as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Achan</hi> did; and warning others not to offend him in like manner, by our Example.</p>
                  <p>And in all theſe caſes, if the <hi>preſent Judgment</hi> be upon ſuch courſes taken, removed; and <hi>Gods Hand turned away</hi> from us: we are our ſelves to take heed we <hi>ſin thus no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto us:</hi> and not provoke him,<note place="margin">John 5.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> (by a feigned humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation whilſt we are under his correcting hand, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of real amendment) to do as he threatens, <hi>i. e. puniſh us ſeven times more,</hi> and augment his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities, till our <hi>wound become incurable,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lev. 26. Jer. 15.18. 2 Chron. 26.16.</note> 
                     <hi>and paſt remedy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">(2. If we be (as in <hi>Epidemical Judgments</hi>) ſufferers in common with others; our duty is, (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſhifting off the blame upon others) each man in particular to own his own ſhare in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon guilt,<note place="margin">1 King. 8.38.</note> (as <hi>knowing the plague of his own heart</hi>) and by true Repentance and amendment to leſſen the publique Load which he hath contributed to greaten; and call on others, as he hath opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to do the like: and laſtly, when he hath ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred himſelf fit for that charitable office to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, by having recovered his own Innocence, to intercede earneſtly and affectionately, (uſing his renewed Intereſt with a reconciled God) for the ſociety to which he doth belong.</p>
                  <p n="3">(3. If we be bare <hi>hearers</hi> or <hi>beholders</hi> of Gods great ſeverities upon others, and <hi>our ſelves free;</hi> we are then,</p>
                  <p n="1">(1.) <hi>Wiſely to conſider his doings:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 64.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> ſo as to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve carefully what of God more than ordinary ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in them: that we may give him the glory of thoſe perfections, which he hath thereby rendred moſt conſpicuous, for which thoſe that <hi>have plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in his works</hi> ſpecially ſtudy them.</p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:45297:34"/>
                  <p n="2">(2.) And particularly, to endeavour to reduce <hi>Gods Providences</hi> of this kind (as well as all others) to the Rule of his <hi>written word;</hi> and obſerve the correſpondency they bear each to other. For this will ſerve us to very great purpoſes, in order to a firm faith in him, and fear of him, when we can ſay,<note place="margin">Lev. 10.3.</note> (with <hi>Moſes</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi>) <hi>This is that which the Lord hath ſaid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">(3.) To <hi>lay them up in memory</hi> as a choice trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to be made uſe of when occaſion ſerves. For God expects his great works ſhould make deep Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions in the minds of men. And therefore ſome Interpreters read that clauſe of <hi>Pſal.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſala 111. <hi>A.</hi> Verſ. Tig.</note> 111. which we render, <hi>He hath made his wonderful works to be remembred, [Memorioe conſecravit]</hi> he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted or conſecrated them to remembrance. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they imply, that it carries in it a kind of <hi>ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege,</hi> to let them ſlip through our memories as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and inconſiderable things. And he takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it himſelf as a great crime in the <hi>Iſraelites, That they remembred not his hand,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 43.</note> 
                     <hi>how he wrought his ſigns in</hi> Egypt, <hi>and his wonders in the field of</hi> Zoan.</p>
                  <p n="4">(4.) And to <hi>improve</hi> that <hi>remembrance,</hi> as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is offered, by applying it to our ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, according to the <hi>ſutableneſs</hi> that thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences bear to the <hi>caſes to which they are applicable.</hi> So when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were apt to be afraid of the mighty and numerous Enemies they were to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, at their entrance into <hi>Canaan;</hi> God ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably recalls to their memories,<note place="margin">Dent. 7.16, 17.</note> 
                     <hi>what he did to</hi> Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aoh <hi>and all</hi> Egypt. And when our <hi>Saviour</hi> would fortifie his Diſciples againſt the Tentations to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with the obſtinate and unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> in holding out the <hi>ſiege of</hi> Jeruſalem, out of affection to their concerns there; having before told them of <hi>that great day of the Revelation of the Son of Man</hi> in his Judgments on that City,<note place="margin">Luke 17.</note> and that there
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:45297:34"/>wanted nothing to compleat its deſtruction in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to <hi>Sodom,</hi> but only the removing the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians thence,<note place="margin">29, 30, 31, 34.</note> (as they went afterwards to <hi>Pella</hi> out of the City) in conformity to <hi>Lots going out of</hi> Sodom: he bids them to <hi>remember</hi> Lots <hi>wife,</hi> whoſe tenderneſs of her concerns in <hi>Sodom,</hi> made her look back, and therefore by Gods juſt Judgment, in the very place, ſhe was turned into a <hi>Statue of Salt.</hi> And the <hi>Pſalmiſt comforted himſelf</hi> againſt Gods preſent Enemies, and their outragious inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences; by <hi>remembring Gods Judgments of old.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.52.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">(5.) And to be ſenſible of the ſpecial <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of God to us, whom, it may be he hath as <hi>ſignally delivered</hi> when we were in equal guilt and danger with others, who no leſs <hi>ſignally periſhed:</hi> yea, poſſibly, when our own Conſciences told us, that we our ſelves better deſerved to have been made Examples of Divine ſeverity, than they that were ſo.</p>
                  <p>Thus the returning <hi>Jews</hi> acknowledge with gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude the Mercy of God to them, that in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezra 9.8.</note> 
                     <hi>he had left them a remnant to eſcape;</hi> and to <hi>give them a nail in his holy place, i. e.</hi> a little, though but a weak faſtning there. And ſo ought all thoſe whom Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have <hi>left,</hi> in publique calamities eſpecially, <hi>like a few gleaning grapes after the Vintage,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 27.6.</note> as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> expreſſeth the ſaid <hi>Remnant</hi> of <hi>returning Jews.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">(6.) To poſſeſs our hearts with a <hi>reverend</hi> and <hi>awful fear</hi> of that God,<note place="margin">Pſ. 66.5.</note> who is <hi>terrible in his doings toward the children of Men.</hi> This uſe <hi>David</hi> made of Gods ſtroke upon <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.9.</note> he was <hi>afraid of the Lord that day.</hi> And the whole Chriſtian Church, yea, the generality of men that heard of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual deaths of <hi>Ananias</hi> and his <hi>wife,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 5.11.</note> (as I before obſerved) were ſurpriſed with <hi>a great fear.</hi> When God as a <hi>Lion,</hi> does but <hi>roar</hi> in his threatnings, <hi>who will not fear?</hi> ſays <hi>Amos,</hi> and much more,<note place="margin">Amos 3.8.</note>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:45297:35"/>when (as his contemporary Prophet expreſſeth it) he <hi>tears like a young Lion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hoſ. 3.14</note> does he expect, certainly, that all men ſhould <hi>ſerve him with fear,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 2.11.</note> and even thoſe that <hi>rejoyce before him,</hi> (in the moſt <hi>feſtival</hi> exerciſes of Religion, wherein <hi>joy</hi> was part of the ſervice required) ſhould do it <hi>with trembling?</hi> Thus are <hi>Chriſtian Gentiles</hi> taught, upon conſideration of the noted ſeverities of God towards his former people the <hi>Jews,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>not to be high-minded, but fear;</hi> as alſo the <hi>Chriſtian Jews,</hi> upon the remembrance of the ſeverities of God towards their fore-fathers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, in the very delivery whereof <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf ſaid, <hi>I exceedingly fear and quake;</hi> are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on by the ſame <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> to <hi>ſerve him with reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and godly fear:</hi> as conſidering, that not only Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> but Mount <hi>Sion</hi> alſo had its thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings, and the Goſpel its terrours, as well as the Law: So that offenders <hi>againſt him that ſpeaks from Heaven,</hi> ſhall not eſcape, more than they that <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed him that ſpake on Earth;</hi> nay, ſhall rather be puniſhed with more ſeverity, becauſe the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1. to v. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> as well as <hi>Jews,</hi> is, if provoked, <hi>a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire;</hi> and not to be met (as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it) by <hi>thorns and briars ſet in array againſt him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 27.4.</note> 
                     <hi>left he go through them, and burn them together.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">(7.) <hi>Laſtly,</hi> to <hi>improve</hi> that <hi>fear</hi> for our future <hi>Caution;</hi> that taking warning by his noted ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties towards others, we give him no occaſion, by the ſame or like provocations, to take us in hand next. But eſpecially, are we to take heed of <hi>thoſe ſins</hi> in particular, againſt which we are evidently convinced God hath given <hi>publique Teſtimonies</hi> by any <hi>remarkable Judgments.</hi> Which is the uſe the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us we ought to make of the great Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, againſt the old <hi>Iſraelites</hi> left us up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Record in Scripture.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om 6. to 11.</note> 
                     <hi>All thoſe things</hi> (which there he reckons up) <hi>befell them,</hi> ſays he, <hi>for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:45297:35"/>and were written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come:</hi> to the intent, as he implies it in ſeveral Inſtances, that we <hi>ſhould not luſt,</hi> or <hi>commit Idolatry,</hi> or <hi>Fornication,</hi> or <hi>tempt Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>murmur,</hi> as they did, for fear of the ſame or like Judgments.</p>
                  <p>And the like End ſurely God aims at, in thoſe Judgments, which fall out in any Age or part of the world, to admoniſh men to repent of, and for the future, abſtain from thoſe Courſes which (as it were) after violence to his Patience and long-fuſſering, and extort thoſe notable ſeverities from him, by the audacious importunity of their noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Impieties.</p>
                  <p>And in all ſuch caſes the <hi>wiſe man</hi> (in <hi>Solomons</hi> Phraſe) <hi>will hear and increaſe in learning,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 1.5.</note> by forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying himſelf againſt all Tentations to thoſe ſins, againſt which he ſeeth the <hi>Hand</hi> of God ſo nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <hi>lifted up.</hi> So that if among all the jolly crew of <hi>ſottiſh drunkards,</hi> but now and then one <hi>break his neck</hi> in his drunkenneſs, or by a <hi>cup-quarrel</hi> loſe his life; (though withal many ſuch ſhould eſcape ſuch ends, even ſo many as to give countenance to the <hi>profane Proverb,</hi> that <hi>drunken men come by no harm</hi>) yet the prudent man will lay thoſe <hi>few</hi> contrary Inſtances to heart; and ſay in himſelf, <hi>Why ſhould I not fear, if I deſpiſe ſuch warnings, that I may be made the next Example in that kind?</hi> If there be a ſignal Inſtance in his Age, and within his obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a noted cruel <hi>oppreſſor,</hi> upon whoſe eſtate and houſe the <hi>curſe</hi> of God remarkably deſcends, ſo that his poſterity are either all <hi>buried in death, i. e.</hi> die obſcurely,<note place="margin">Job 27.15, &amp;c.</note> ſo as to be miſſed by ſcarce any body: or if any of them ſurvive, they are <hi>not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with bread;</hi> but the great eſtates gotten by unlawful means, melt away like wax before the Sun, e're inherited by the <hi>third Generation;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 3.31, 33.</note> the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:45297:36"/>ſerious obſerver will learn, not to <hi>envy him, nor chooſe any of his ways.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the Examples ſhould be more rare, than in theſe days they are,<note place="margin">Luke 15.30.</note> of a debauched <hi>Prodigal, ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all his living with harlots,</hi> and by means of whoriſh women reduced from an ample Eſtate to a <hi>piece of bread:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 6.26.</note> or of ſome ſinners in the ſame kind,<note place="margin">Prov. 5.11.</note> whoſe <hi>fleſh and body are conſumed with a loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom diſeaſe,</hi> thereby <hi>receiving in themſelves</hi> (in the Phraſe of the Apoſtle, concerning uncleanneſs in another kind) <hi>that recompence of their errour which was meet:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 1.27.</note> the conſidering man will ſay with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>What ſecurity have I, that the ſame ſin, if I follow it, will not reduce me to the ſame Caſe?</hi> If but <hi>the field of a ſluggard be overgrown with thorns, and nettles cover the face thereof,</hi> &amp;c. (<hi>i. e.</hi> his worldly eſtate goes backward for want of honeſt Induſtry) a wiſe <hi>Solomon will conſider it,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 25.32.</note> 
                     <hi>and receive inſtruction.</hi> If the daring and audacious <hi>Appeals</hi> of a bold ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to God in fearful <hi>Curſes</hi> upon himſelf; or profane affectations of a new uncouth way of gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, by inventing <hi>new Imprecations</hi> againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: or the malicious ſhooting of <hi>bitter words</hi> as <hi>arrows</hi> in evil wiſhes againſt others; amongſt men that <hi>love curſing,</hi> do but once or twice in an Age meet with a ſutable ſtroke of Divine ſeverity, and <hi>curſing come into the curſers bowels like water,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 109.18.</note> 
                     <hi>and as oyl into his bones:</hi> a conſiderate Chriſtian will take heed,<note place="margin">Pſ. 39.1.</note> that he <hi>offend not thus with his tongue;</hi> and by a ſolemn purpoſe, <hi>as with a bridle, keep his mouth from tranſgreſſing</hi> in that manner.</p>
                  <p>In a word, when all the <hi>places</hi> of <hi>Execution</hi> in a Nation become <hi>Pulpits,</hi> whence the miſerable Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors from their own woful experience, preach <hi>Recantation Sermons,</hi> wherein they renounce the evil Principles they have lived by, and warn all men of the dangerous conſequences of licentious and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:45297:36"/>Courſes: and the ſame Doctrine be alſo as frequently preached from the <hi>death-beds</hi> of other ſinners, wherein the <hi>curſes written in Gods book</hi> are verified in the eyes and ears of all men, except they wilfully ſhut them both: who, but a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately forlorn wretch, will dare <hi>ſay in his heart, I ſhall have peace,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 29.19, 20.</note> 
                     <hi>though I walk in the imagination of mine own heart: i. e.</hi> gratifie my own ſinful inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to ſatiety, as one that <hi>adds drunkenneſs to thirſt?</hi> Againſt ſuch an one, ſurely, (if any ſuch there be) <hi>the anger of the Lord and his jealouſie may well ſmoke,</hi> yea and <hi>burn</hi> (as he elſewhere threatens) <hi>to the loweſt Hell;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">32.22.</note> the place appointed for them (ſays the Verſe following my Text) that under ſuch evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>tokens</hi> to <hi>remember</hi> him by, <hi>forget God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 9.17.</note> And juſtly may God make them <hi>Examples themſelves,</hi> whom the <hi>Examples</hi> of <hi>others</hi> will not amend: as being guilty of tempting his <hi>Juſtice</hi> beyond all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of forbearance, by the ungrateful abuſing of that <hi>Patience</hi> that ſhould have <hi>led them to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> of daring <hi>preſumption</hi> upon that lenity and goodneſs which only hath given them that merciful reprieve,<note place="margin">Pſ. 66.9.</note> by which their forfeited <hi>ſouls are held in life;</hi> of monſtrous <hi>hardneſs</hi> and <hi>impenitency of heart, whereby they treaſure up to themſelves wrath againſt the day of wrath,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 2.5.</note> 
                     <hi>and the revelation of the righteous Judgment of God;</hi> and laſtly, of prodigious <hi>mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and deſperate <hi>foolhardineſs,</hi> when as (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the fearful Inſtances in all Ages by which God hath taught the world that <hi>none ever hardned himſelf againſt him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job 9.4.</note> 
                     <hi>and proſpered,</hi> yet) as if they would wreſtle a fall, or fight a duel with the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, <hi>they run upon him even on his neck,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh 1 15.25, 26.</note> 
                     <hi>and on the thick boſſes of his bucklers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Believe it, ſinner, believe it, (for Truth it ſelf hath ſpoken it) though God ſpare thee a while,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.11.</note>
                     <note place="margin">Neh. 9.17</note> and <hi>execute not ſentence ſpeedily againſt thy wicked
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:45297:37"/>works;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 9.22.</note> though he be <hi>ſlow to anger, and endure with much long-ſuffering the Veſſels of wrath fitted for deſtruction;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.9.</note> as not <hi>being willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance:</hi> yet will he not finally ſuffer his holy ſpirit to be vexed, his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to be trampled upon, his word and its warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to be deſpiſed, and his Exemplary Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be entertained only as news without any farther effect; but <hi>if the wicked turn not, he will whet his Sword,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 7.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.13.</note> 
                     <hi>he will bend his bow and make it ready, and prepare for him the Inſtruments of death:</hi> and (when he hath <hi>ſtirred up all his wrath,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.38.</note> which yet in his <hi>great compaſſion he</hi> forbears) he will <hi>wound the head of his Enemies,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 68.21.</note> 
                     <hi>and the hairy ſcalp of all ſuch as go on ſtill in their treſpaſſes;</hi> and either here or hereafter make them feel by experience, who without feeling would not believe it, what a <hi>fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing it is to fall into the hands of the living God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 10.31.</note> From which doleful experience God keep us all, for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:45297:37"/>
                  <p>A Juſt NARRATIVE, OR, ACCOUNT Of the Man whoſe <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Legs rotted off:</hi> In the Pariſh of <hi>KINGS-SWINFORD,</hi> IN <hi>STAFFORD-SHIRE,</hi> Where he died, <hi>June</hi> 21. 1677.</p>
                  <p>Carefully Collected by <hi>JA. ILLINGWORTH,</hi> B. D. An Eye and Ear-Witneſs of moſt of the material Paſſages in it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>A.C.</hi> for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the Gun at the Weſt-end of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1678.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:45297:38"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45297:38"/>
                  <head>To the Reverend S. FORD. D. D. Rector of <hi>Old-Swinford</hi> in <hi>Worceſterſhire.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>BEing importuned by divers (Gentlemen, Miniſters, and others of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood) to draw up a full <hi>Narrative</hi> and <hi>Account</hi> of that late <hi>ſad Providence</hi> (which hath filled the hearts and mouths of the Country round about us, the ſame whereof is alſo ſpread into remote parts) I was at laſt prevailed with to endeavour their ſatisfaction: And the rather becauſe of a general <hi>rumour</hi> in the Country, <hi>that the man had declared ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral things to me of near concernment to himſelf, which he concealed from all other Viſitants.</hi> That I might not therefore ſuffer ſuch Reports to paſs uncertain, nor be wanting in that which was by ſome urged as my duty; I did (by travelling, at ſeveral times, above <hi>ſixty miles</hi> in the parts adjacent) enquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to divers particular circumſtances, which I was not before fully clear in: and have now at laſt ſet all down in plain words (ſutable to ſuch an account) that the meaneſt concerned to
<pb facs="tcp:45297:39"/>know and make good uſe of the providence, might at firſt reading clearly underſtand it.</p>
                  <p>Sir, That I addreſs this to you, is, that I may take an opportunity to make my hearty ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments for your learned and uſeful <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit</hi> upon this occaſion, to the general ſatisfaction of your Hearers; and I muſt in my own name, and many of theirs, intreat, you would make the ſubſtance of them more publick from the <hi>Preſs,</hi> that the <hi>Readers</hi> may learn not to be too <hi>cenſorious</hi> in things of this nature, not yet to paſs by ſo ſignal a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence without that juſt <hi>Obſervation</hi> it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, and due <hi>reverence</hi> toward that <hi>God</hi> who <hi>is known by the Judgments which he executeth,</hi> as you have fully ſhewed us. I hope, Sir, I invite you to nothing, but what your own Judgment accounts worthy your labour; and I am confident it will be no mean addition to your former elaborate ſervices of God and his Church. In which that you may be long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for his Glory, and the good of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſhall be the hearty Prayer of (Reverend Sir)</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your moſt affectionate (though unworthy Friend) to honour and ſerve you, <hi>J. ILLINGWORTH.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45297:39"/>
                  <head>A juſt <hi>Narrative</hi> or <hi>Account</hi> of the Man whoſe <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Legs Rotted off</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Kings-Swinford</hi> in <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire,</hi> where he Died, <hi>June 21. 1677.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>RIchard Duncalf</hi> of <hi>Godſal</hi> Pariſh, not far from <hi>Wolverhampton,</hi> in the County of <hi>Stafford,</hi> dying many years ſince (and his Wife al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo) left behind them many Children, and but ſlender proviſion for them.</p>
                  <p>One of their Sons, <hi>John Duncalf,</hi> bound himſelf an Apprentice to <hi>Thomas Gibbons</hi> of <hi>Kings-Swinford</hi> in the ſame County, Wheelwright. When he had ſerved his Maſter two years and ſeven months (or thereabouts) he and his fellow Apprentice ſtealing from their Maſter a conſiderable quantity of Iron, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered it to a third perſon, who promiſed to conceal it from their Maſter: but being all brought before the Right Honorable the Lord <hi>Ward</hi> of <hi>Dudley-Caſtle,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on examination ſeverally, they accuſed each other, and confeſſed the whole: By which means there was found concealed (as <hi>Tho. Gibbons</hi> ſaith) 26 pound of old Iron, beſides more that was wrought up, new Waggon-Nails, ends of Bars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Upon their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion the Lord <hi>Ward</hi> ſent them to the Houſe of Correction, about <hi>October</hi> 14. 1675. But the other Apprentice being dangerouſly ſick there, and this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45297:40"/>
                     <hi>John Duncalf</hi> pretending, at leaſt, to be ſick alſo, they two were ſet at liberty the week foll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ng. After which time this ſaid <hi>John Duncalf</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to ☞ come again to his former ſervice (ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>, he would never ſet his feet in <hi>Kings-Swinford</hi> whilſt he lived) but offering and engaging to pay to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter each other: by which means this young man (who was then full twenty years of age, and at more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty than formerly whilſt an Apprentice) gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf up to licentious courſes, <hi>viz.</hi> (as he confeſſed to me, <hi>April</hi> 26.1677) to <hi>Idleneſs, Stealing, Lying, Curſing, Swearing, Drunkenneſs, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs with Women. Which laſt,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>was not by committing actual Fornication or Adultery, but in the thoughts of his heart, and by laſcivious words, and geſtures, whereby he had endeavoured to tempt them to lewdneſs in divers places.</hi> I muſt therefore here clear my ſelf and him from an unjuſt rumour and report common (as I am infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) in the Country hereabouts, which many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple yet believe, <hi>viz. [That he confeſſed ſome things to me which he deſired might be concealed whilſt he lived,</hi> as, <hi>that he had committed a Rape upon a young perſon, and afterward murdered her: That he was guilty of Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, or lying with Beaſts,</hi> &amp;c.] I do therefore openly declare to all, that theſe were groundleſs rumors or reports, and I do aſſure them he never deſired me to conceal any thing he ſaid or confeſſed to me, nor did he ever ſpeak to me of any ſuch things as theſe which ſome have reported and others believed. But the faults above-mentioned ſeemed to lie as an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burden upon his Conſcience, when he judged Gods hand was ſeverely chaſtizing him for them, and all his other impieties; among which his conſtant <hi>profaneneſs</hi> had not been the leaſt, in that, <hi>although he could both read and write, yet he had</hi> (as he ſaid to me)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45297:40"/>
                     <hi>a long time neglected all manner of Service and Worſhip of God, as well on the Lords day as other days, and that both in private and publick.</hi> It is ſaid, he <hi>ſtole</hi> many things to ſupply his growing neceſſities (which his idleneſs and intemperance brought upon him) chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Bibles;</hi> and the rather becauſe they would ſooneſt be bought by others. About <hi>January</hi> the 6th. 1676/7 coming to the houſe of <hi>Humphrey Babb,</hi> living at the <hi>Grange-mill,</hi> about three miles from <hi>Wolverhampton,</hi> he begged of <hi>Margaret,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Humphrey</hi>'s Wife, Victuals and ſmall drink. The Woman having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly known him, and compaſſionating his preſent condition, gave him freely ſuch as ſhe had, but whilſt ſhe ſtooped to draw drink for him, he <hi>ſtole her Bible,</hi> (as he confeſſed to her afterwards.) This <hi>Bible</hi> he ſold for three ſhillings to a Maid of <hi>John Downings,</hi> who lives near the <hi>Heath-Forge,</hi> not far from the place where he ſtole it. By which means, not long after, <hi>Humphrey Babb</hi>'s Wife heard of her Bible, demanded it of the Maid that bought it, and making her ſome allowance toward what ſhe paid for it, received it again long before either of them ſaw him, or heard what was become of him: But this being noiſed in the Country thereabouts, one <hi>Henry Evans</hi> told his Father <hi>Thomas Evans</hi> (commonly called <hi>Painter</hi>) who lives near <hi>Henly</hi> or <hi>Himley</hi> (they both knew him) what <hi>John Duncalf</hi> had done: at which the ſaid <hi>John Duncalf,</hi> when he heard of it, was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry angry, and gave out threatning words againſt the young man; but being charged with it by them, he did not only deny it with ſome fierceneſs, but execrated and curſed himſelf, <hi>wiſhing his hands might rot off,</hi> if that were true (as the ſaid <hi>Thomas Evans</hi> teſtifies) and <hi>John Bennet</hi> his Keeper, ſaith, he often heard him ſay to Gentlemen that viſited him in his ſickneſs, that he did ſo curſe himſelf upon that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45297:41"/>to <hi>Thomas Evans.</hi> And this he acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his own accord, to me and many others, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times, when he ſeemed moſt ſerious and in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt <hi>[That he ſo curſed himſelf, and that immediately upon the execration or curſing of himſelf, he had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward horror or trembling upon him, a dread and fear of the Divine Majeſty, and Juſtice of God, which fear and working of his Conſcience continued more or leſs many days after.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When I asked him (upon this ingenious acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment) <hi>why he did not confeſs his wickedneſs, and endeavour that the Bible might be reſtored to the owner?</hi> his anſwer was, <hi>[That the Devil and his own heart would not ſuffer him.]</hi> Yet this he acknowledged to me <hi>[That within a few days after that execration his fleſh began to look black at the wriſts of his hands, and ſo continued divers weeks before it did ſenſibly rot.]</hi> He went then and wrought with one <hi>Thomas Osborn</hi> a Joyner in <hi>Dudley,</hi> and (as <hi>Osborn</hi> ſaith) continued with him about a fortnight (Shrovetueſday being the laſt day as he well remembers) and that it was the laſt work that ever he did; which I cannot won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at, conſidering what this poor man ſaid to me concerning himſelf in reference to that time, <hi>viz.</hi> [<hi>After I had curſed my ſelf about the Bible, I wrought with a</hi> Joyner <hi>at</hi> Dudley; <hi>but at that time I had a fear and trembling upon me, which frequently troubled me, and made me have no great mind to work; and ſo feeling my ſelf weak and faint, and fearing an Ague or Fever, I went towards my acquaintance, but in the way finding I was unable to go any further, I laid my ſelf down in a Barn</hi> (<hi>at</hi> Parton-Hall <hi>as I remember</hi>) <hi>belonging to Sir</hi> Walter Wroteſeley, <hi>and there continued two days and nights before I was found</hi>] (ſome ſay he ſaid (at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times) from <hi>Tueſday</hi> night to <hi>Friday</hi> morning.) Being found, he was kept at the charge of the Pariſh of <hi>Tettenhal</hi> (in which <hi>Parton-Hall</hi> ſtands) until
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45297:41"/>the next monthly meeting of the <hi>Juſtices</hi> of the Peace, who (<hi>March</hi> 27. 1677.) by examination finding <hi>Kings-Swinford</hi> to have been the laſt place of his ſettlement, made an order he ſhould be carried thither, and maintained by that Pariſh. There he was received, <hi>March</hi> 28. and <hi>John Bennet</hi> appointed to take care of him: firſt in a Barn belonging to the <hi>three Crowns,</hi> (an Inn ſtanding on the Road between <hi>Wolverhampton</hi> and <hi>Kidderminſter</hi>) and after one fortnight removed by the Overſeers for the Poor, to the dwelling houſe of the ſaid <hi>John Bennet</hi> his Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in <hi>Wall-Heath-ſide.</hi> His fleſh at firſt began to riſe in great lumps or knots at the wriſts of his hands, and at his knees (as his Keeper tells me) and after a little time to break and run, and ſhortly after to ſhrink from the bones at thoſe places, at which time, white putrid matter came out and ran abundantly, cauſing exquiſite pain and torment to this poor man: And ſo offenſive was the ſmell for ſeveral weeks together, that thoſe who came to viſit him who were not only many hundreds, but, 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, thouſands (his Keeper and Neighbours ſay many thouſands) were not able to abide in the room with him, nor ſtand near without the door, except they had herbs or other things at their mouths and noſes to ſmell to. The Viſitants being ſo numerous at all times of the day, eſpecially on the Lords-days, it ſeemed to give him great diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, and made him very unwilling to talk many times, or anſwer them any thing. They moved him once ſo far to impatience, when they crowded about him each with a queſtion, having Herbs, and other things at their Noſes, that his paſſion made him to forget his own condition, and wiſh <hi>their Noſes might rot off</hi> (as divers there preſent aſſured me;) for which I gently, but ſeriouſly, reproved him at my next viſit. He ſeemed to take the reproof well, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45297:42"/>the fault of his paſſionate expreſſions towards them (provoked as he ſaid, by their crowd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, impertinent curioſity, and fooliſh queſtions; or to that effect:) But he had forgot, or would not confeſs, that he uſed thoſe words,—about <hi>their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes rotting off.</hi>]</p>
                  <p>But his Keeper tells me, he would often be very impatient towards the multitude, and call to him, ſaying, <hi>John, why doſt thou not daſh out their teeth? doeſt thou not ſee how they grin at me?</hi> and the like.</p>
                  <p>About the twentieth of <hi>April</hi> many little Worms came out of the rotten fleſh, ſuch as are uſually ſeen in dead Corpſes (as his Keeper told me) but after he was well waſhed and cleanſed, thoſe ceaſed, and the room and ſmell was nothing ſo offenſive as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly: yet all that while (though it was rumor'd in the Country) he would never confeſs his execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and wiſhes againſt himſelf, until his Keeper de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to eaſe him of the Vermin, Lice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his ſhirt and doublet, and continually tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> promiſed, that if his Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and cleanſe him, (he had long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> all the hair of his head) he would ackno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>, the whole truth, which he then did in ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> as is before related.</p>
                  <p>And now he began to beg inſtruction, and help to repent and that ſome Miniſters and others, who came to viſit him, would pray for and with him, which many did, both publick Preachers and others, at ſeveral times; and ſome who lived near him (as I did) often. Being asked by me what he deſired might be begged of God for him, he returned an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this purpoſe: <hi>That God would give him repentance, and pardon his ſins above-mentioned,</hi> viz. <hi>Idleneſs, Stealing, Lying, Curſing, Swearing, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, unclean Thoughts, and conſtant Prophaneneſs,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45297:42"/>
                     <hi>that he would ſave him for Chriſts ſake, and give him patience in the mean time.</hi>] I did accordingly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to repreſent his caſe before God, and with humble earneſtneſs to pray for mercy for him; and he ſeemed at that time to be ſomewhat affected with the Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was about this time, if I miſtake not, that he ſent for <hi>Humphrey Babb</hi>'s Wife, from whom he ſtole the Bible, ſhe came and brought the Maid he ſold it to, along with her: to them he confeſſed the wrong he had done, and deſired they would forgive him; which the Wife told me ſhe did heartily, and prayed God to forgive hin as ſhe did. The Maid ſeemed to be of the ſame mind and Chriſtian temper.</p>
                  <p>Very many (as I hinted before) hearing of him, came from all parts adjacent, and ſome from places far diſtant, to ſee this ſad ſpectacle of Divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: and amongſt the reſt, ſome of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> one of which, he and his Keeper ſuppoſed to be a <hi>Prieſt</hi> of that profeſſion, who was earneſt with him to renounce his Religion, and become a <hi>Catholick</hi> (as he called it) and they would remove him, take care to heal his Sores, and (ſaid the man, whom they ſuppoſed to be the Prieſt) <hi>I will pawn my ſoul for</hi> ☜ <hi>thine, that thou ſhalt be ſaved:</hi> which I am informed, is an ordinary form of ſpeech amongſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> of this Countrey, when they would perſuade men to their party. When I enquired of this poor man (to try him) <hi>why he did not accept of their offers?</hi> he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to this purpoſe, <hi>[To what end? How can he pawn his ſoul for mine? none can ſave me but Chriſt.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Others who had occaſion to travel this way from <hi>London,</hi> and other parts far off, Weſt and North, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited him, we hope not to ſatisfie their curioſity ſo much, as to behold a monument of Divine ſeverity, and that they might bear witneſs, that <hi>although ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt an evil work is not always executed ſpeedily,</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45297:43"/>yet, <hi>God leaves not himſelf without witneſs,</hi> in this, as well as former ages, againſt Atheiſm and grand impiety.</p>
                  <p>Upon the eighth of <hi>May</hi> following, both his legs were fallen off at the knees, which the poor man perceived not until his Keeper told him and ſhewed them to him, holding them up in his hands, and his right hand, hanging only by ſome ligament, by a little touch of a knife, was taken off alſo: The other hand at the ſame time being black as a ſhooe, and not much unlike, in the fancy of ſome, for roughneſs and hardneſs, to the outſide of a dried Neats-tongue. This hand hanged on a long time after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by ſome ſuch thing as the former, and might ('tis poſſible) have continued in that manner until his death, if he had not deſired his Keeper to take that away alſo as the former, becauſe it was troubleſome to him. Now although putrid matter frequently iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued out at thoſe places, yet he had not ſo much pain as he had formerly for a <hi>month</hi> or <hi>ſix weeks,</hi> as he freely confeſſed; and acknowledged that his ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach was good, and did digeſt ſuch meats as he took, and that he had evacuations by ſiege and urine, as heretofore in his health.</p>
                  <p>So that, continuing in this condition ſome weeks, many began to think the Iſſues might be ſtopped, and his life preſerved many years, if regularly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. Some the Pariſhioners were moved in it, that Phyſicians and Surgeons might be conſulted, and good advice taken in the caſe; but I cannot learn that any thing was done about it, being judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by ſome, incurable. It is ſaid that he expreſſed himſelf to ſome that viſited him in this manner. [That <hi>now the curſe wherewith he had curſed himſelf being fully come to paſs (in that his hands were rotted off) he was perſuaded it would go no further.</hi>] But he forgot that God puniſhed him, not for that ſin only,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45297:43"/>but, for all his great tranſgreſſions (though for that chiefly) as he formerly confeſſed to me, he believed. At laſt his fleſh began to waſt, and his ſpirits to fail; ſo that viſiting him again, and obſerving ſome change in his fleſh and countenance more than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, I laboured to convince him more fully of his condition, and to perſuade him to look up to the great Phyſician, in whoſe hands are the iſſues of life and death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He ſeemed to give diligent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and earneſtly deſired me to pray with him; after prayers, when I was about to leave him for that time, he deſired I would not forget him in my prayers; making it alſo his earneſt requeſt, that I would come again when ever he ſhould ſend for me, which I promiſed I would at any hour day or night. This was <hi>June</hi> 16. and on the 19. (as his Keeper ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth) he was in great anguiſh and trouble of mind, crying out <hi>[What ſhall I do to ſave my poor ſoul?]</hi> with many other expreſſions to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; being very ſick, and fearing his approaching death. But upon what account his Keeper would not ſend for me (in whoſe hearing he ſo earneſtly deſired me to come to him) he knows beſt, and muſt anſwer it, if it was his fault for private reſpects, as is conjectured. On <hi>June</hi> 21. in the morning, I went again to viſit him, unſent for, but found him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible, and paſt any further advice. I ſtaid by him until almoſt noon. He lay ſtill, with his eyes fixed, as a dying man, moved not at any thing we ſaid to him, but upon pouring into him a little drink with a ſpoon at ſeveral times, he coughed a little, and groaned, and then lay as before. When I ſaw there was no probability he would underſtand any thing I ſaid, I left him (after prayer made for him with the company there preſent, in the houſe) and had notice brought me, that he died about two hours after my departure from him.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:45297:44"/>
                  <p>Before I ſum up the whole of this Narrative, and account of his condition, I judge it may be accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Reader to inſert ſome ſhort Obſervations, communicated to me by an ingenious Gentleman, our Neighbour, who ſeveral times viſited him in his affliction. Take them therefore in his own words.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>When I firſt ſaw this young man (which was quickly after he was brought into <hi>Kings-Swinford</hi>) he appeared to me to be of a vigorous ſtate of body, and of an healthy conſtitution, ſaving the ſtrange defect under which he laboured, his hands and legs being then deprived of ſenſe and motion. I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved them, and handled him: They were from both wriſts and knees blackiſh and dying; and I took notice, that about each wriſt and knee there was as it were a <hi>Circle</hi> at the joynt that divided the ſound from the dying parts, and ſeemed like a ligature, prohibiting any nouriſhment to paſs thoſe bounds; ſo that the blood and ſpirits being won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully ſtopped in their circulation, it muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follow, that the parts thus deprived of their wonted ſupply, muſt wither and die as a leaf in Autumn: which ſad progreſs they made till both hands and legs from the wriſts and knees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came dead and dried, black and hard, like Mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, before they fell off at the joynts, which they afterward did. I alſo obſerved, that at the firſt, above each of the forementioned circles, there brake out a ſore, at which the nouriſhing juyce (deſigned by nature to have fed thoſe parts) em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptied it ſelf (now in thoſe ſores corrupted) in a <hi>quitture</hi> or <hi>ſanies,</hi> ſo horribly ſtinking, that few of his Viſitants could well endure the room without ſome ſtrong ſmelling defenſative. But viſiting him after thoſe dead limbs were fallen from the body (all but one hand which was almoſt ſevered) I ſaw the joynts with the fleſh look well and heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45297:44"/>They ſeemed to me free and untouch'd by the former mortification, being quick and ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that now the fellow complained upon the leaſt touch thereof, yet ſeeming to promiſe an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie cure, for that ichorous ſtinking humor was gone; the fleſh was raw, but ſweet, and here and there beſmeared with a thick corrupt <hi>pus,</hi> an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging ſign (ſay Artiſts) that ſores incline to healing: But this poor creature wanting all help from Art or Medicine, ſave what the application of the leaves of Mullein afforded, which by his Keeper were uſed to defend the raw parts; in ſome weeks there iſſued the like thin and ſtinking hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor as before, which ſoon put a period to his life.</q> 
                     <hi>So far my Friend.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to the young man himſelf, he was (as he told me a few days before he died) about <hi>twenty two</hi> years of age. It was eaſie to obſerve, he had been a ſtrong young man, naturally of a ſtubborn tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, much hardened by evil courſes; yet he ſeemed ſometimes to be affected with his condition, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes made to him, and prayers with him; and I wiſh I might have had from him as clear an evidence of a comfortable change wrought in him, as I would gladly have told the world. I muſt in charity leave his final condition to God, who thus afflicted and chaſtized him for the ſpace of near about <hi>four months,</hi> that he might be a ſignal ſpectacle to thouſands, of Gods diſpleaſure againſt impiety.</p>
                  <p>The ſum of all is this, That a ſtrong, luſty, young man, as moſt in the County where he was born, being unfaithful to God and his Maſter, and giving himſelf to licentiouſneſs and wickedneſs, was brought to a morſel of bread; and by doing evil and denying it with execrations, had a ſting and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret remorſe in his conſcience, by which, and want (the fruit of his idleneſs and intemperance) he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45297:45"/>grew faint and weak, and his hands waxed feeble: not being able to work, deſigned to betake himſelf to his Friends, but was ſtopped by the way, forced to lie down under the hand of God, that the <hi>Curſe</hi> wherewith he had curſed himſelf might <hi>come upon him;</hi> and ſo by the ſtupendious providence of God he was made a ſpectacle to the world of Divine ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity many weeks, that others might <hi>ſee, and hear, and fear, and do no more wickedly.</hi> And I wiſh, God may have no reaſon to ſay to any, (as by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in another caſe,<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 13.41.</note>)—<hi>Behold ye deſpiſers, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and periſh: for I work a work in your days, which you ſhall in no wiſe believe, though a man declare it unto you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:45297:45"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Being requeſted by Mr.</hi> Illing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth <hi>to give you an account of what I am able to ſay concerning</hi> John Duncalf, <hi>I apprehend the beſt way is by a bare and brief</hi> Narrative <hi>of that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe that paſſed between us whilſt I was with him; if there is any thing worth your cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance, you may make uſe of it as you pleaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our Diſcourſe was as followeth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>May</hi> 1ſt. 1677.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>SPeaking to him of the deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rableneſs of his Condition, and that ſure there was a more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary hand of Gods Providence in it ariſing from ſome evil actor actions of his.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45297:46"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Anſwered yes, 'twas for his ſins.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>When I told him that ſin was generally the procuring Cauſe of every mans ſufferings; but under ſuch remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable and dreadful ſufferings as theſe were, there is uſually one or more ſpecial ſins to be inquired after, as the neareſt procuring Cauſe or Cauſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> He anſwered yes; ſo it was in his caſe. He ſtole a Bible from a Woman, and being charged with it, denied it with this fearful wiſh, <hi>[That his Hands might rot off if he ſtole it.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>Then I asked him, whether his hands began to blacken, or change Colour, or tingle,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>preſently after the impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or that fearful wiſh of his?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Anſwer'd no; but his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tingled ſadly.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. John, <hi>how long was it e're your hands began to rot, or had any ſigns of putrefaction upon them after the Curſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> About a fortnight.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45297:46"/>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>Have you made your peace with God for ſo great an offence?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> [Being a man not apt to ſpeak, and ignorant withal] made little anſwer, only ſhaked his head.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>Have you asked the Woman forgiveneſs, and to your power endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make ſatisfaction; or if the Bible were in your hands, to make Reſtitution?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, he did ſend for her, and ſhe came accordingly, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God forgive him, for ſhe did.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. John, <hi>canſt pray? I have not found in thee any motions or inclinations thereunto ſince I came.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Shakes his head again, and nothing he ſaid.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. John, <hi>doſt thou know how at ſo great a diſtance as ſin hath made thee, to go to the Father?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, by Jeſus Chriſt, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpering it ſoftly, yet ſo as I might hear him.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>Then fearing he did not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what Chriſt hath done for the World, I very briefly opened to him the Tenor and
<pb facs="tcp:45297:47"/>Conditions of the Covenant of Grace, and ſo how he muſt expect Mercy at the hands of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Then (ſo far as I could gueſs) he began ſomewhat to relent, for the Tears trickled down his cheeks, and many Symptoms of conviction and ſorrow ſeemed to be upon him; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe words, or to this purpoſe: For Gods ſake, Sir, pray for me.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. John, <hi>I am glad to ſee ſome, though the leaſt tokens of penitence in thee — The Lord enlarge thine heart, and make thy Conſcience tender — I am willing,</hi> John, <hi>to pray for thee, and ſo I perceive is this whole company: But it would be great ſatisfaction to us, if you would acquaint us, what we ſhould more particularly deſire of God on your account.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Good Sir, that my ſins may be pardoned, as loſs of Time, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Duty, and the ſervice of God.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>Is not Sabbath-breaking one?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> O yes, yes!</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>Have you any thing elſe to ſay?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> No. Then let us pray. —</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45297:47"/>
                  <p>Ending with the Lords Prayer, he repeated the Petitions after me, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Amen,</hi> with ſomewhat an elevated voice; being obſerved to weep ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times whilſt we continued prayer.</p>
                  <p>After which I parted with him, making me to promiſe him the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of my Prayers.</p>
                  <p>About a fortnight after he ſends a Meſſenger to me to tell me he deſired my company again; at which time I made it my buſineſs not ſo much to ask him Queſtions, as to inform him of thoſe Truths that as I thought had a neceſſary conducency to our eternal peace. [Spending ſome hours with him that day, as I could bear the noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom ſtench that then came from him.] Before I came away that time, which was the laſt time that I ſaw him; his Keeper told me, that a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſt had been with him ſome few days before, earneſtly endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to proſelyte him to their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; uſing this Argument: That if he would turn <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> I will
<pb facs="tcp:45297:48"/>pawn my Soul to thy Soul thou ſhalt be ſaved. But all he could obtain of the poor man, was only this, that he would conſider of it. Then asking <hi>John Duncalf,</hi> whether this was true? He anſwered, Yes. Praying with him, I took my final leave and fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well. This is all (worthy Sir) that I know concerning him. I can only add that I am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>JONATH. NEWEY.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Kinfare,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>Aug.</hi> 17. 1677.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:45297:48"/>
                  <p>WE whoſe Names are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſubſcribed, living in the Neighbourhood of <hi>Kings-Swinford,</hi> where <hi>John Duncalf</hi> the ſubject of the preceding <hi>Narrative,</hi> whilſt Gods hand was ſo ſeverely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, for the moſt part reſided; and having moſt of us viſited him and diſcourſed him in that condition, and the reſt of us received frequent Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the Paſſages herein men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned from a multitude of credible Witneſſes; do (in order to the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring ſo uſeful a <hi>Relation</hi> more credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſo far as we are known) atteſt, that we judge it to be very exactly and impartially penned in all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars: and eſpecially, in thoſe Paſſages of it which contain the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent <hi>ſerious acknowledgements</hi> of the mentioned <hi>John Duncalf, (That he did imprecate that Judgment upon himſelf which is here expreſſed, and upon the occaſion here related)</hi> which he made
<pb facs="tcp:45297:49"/>not only in the hearing of the Author, but alſo of moſt of us: as alſo, in the ſubſtance of thoſe that relate the <hi>rotting off of his Hands and Legs</hi> before his death, in the manner herein men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. And this <hi>atteſtation</hi> we make with no other deſign, but that God may have the glory, and the world the benefit of ſo <hi>Exemplary a Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> For which end we as heartily accompany this <hi>Narrative</hi> with our prayers, as with our hands.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Simon Ford,</hi> D. D.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Tho. Wilsby.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Amb. Sparry.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Raynolds.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Samuel Mountfort.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Edward Paget.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:45297:49"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
